<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The heroine musqueteer: or, the female warrier A true history: very delightful, and full of pleasant adventures in the campagnes of 1676, &amp; 1677. Translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Héroïne mousquetaire. English</title>
            <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3208B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895334</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895334</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2317:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The heroine musqueteer: or, the female warrier A true history: very delightful, and full of pleasant adventures in the campagnes of 1676, &amp; 1677. Translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Héroïne mousquetaire. English</title>
                  <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 236 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for James Mages and Richard Bentley, in Russel-street in Covent-Garden, near the Piazza's, and Richard Tonson near Grays-In-Gate in Grays-In-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Préchac, Jean de.  L'héroine mousquetaire.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
                  <note>Identified by ESTC as Wing (CD-ROM, 1996) P3206.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152700:1"/>
            <p>THE Heroine Muſqueteer: OR, THE FEMALE Warrier. A TRUE HISTORY: Very delightful, and full of Pleaſant Adventures in the Campagnes of 1676, &amp; 1677.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of</hi> French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>James Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> and <hi>Richard Bentley,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> near the <hi>Piazza</hi>'s, and <hi>Richard Tonſon</hi> near <hi>Grays-In-Gate</hi> in <hi>Grays-In-Lane.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152700:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152700:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Count <hi>De Louvigny,</hi> Governor of <hi>Navar</hi> &amp; <hi>Bearn.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN making you a Preſent of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roine Muſqueteer,</hi> I do but reſtore you what already belongs to you: <hi>Bearn,</hi> where ſhe was born, is a Province ſo ſenſible of its Real Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations
<pb facs="tcp:152700:3"/>to my Lord Marſhal, your Father, and You, that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours paid you as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of your Country, exceed thoſe they owe you as Governours of it. The kindneſs you have for the Province in general, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly for thoſe of <hi>Bearn,</hi> is ſo well known, that many younger Brothers quit their Fathers Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with incredible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,
<pb facs="tcp:152700:3"/>and run com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly into the Armies, without any thing to truſt to but your Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which generally proves more uſeful to them than their Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, by your bounty and liberality to ſuch as are in need of it, and the Favours and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments you help them to who deſerve it. This, my Lord, gives me hopes you will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe
<pb facs="tcp:152700:4"/>your Protection to a <hi>Heroine</hi> you have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in the ſervice by the Fame of your Great Actions in <hi>Poland, Flanders, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> which ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs only and infirmities have been able to put a ſtop to. My intereſt, (had I no other reaſons, would have ingag'd me to pay you this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, the beſt defence I could provide for my
<pb facs="tcp:152700:4"/>
               <hi>Book,</hi> being the prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Name to it. It belongs properly to the Juriſdiction of the Fair Sex to paſs ſentence on Works of this Nature; and I have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve my little Story, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of a Perſon of your Quality (who are not only the greateſt Gallant of the Court, but have the beſt Meen, and are moſt in favour
<pb facs="tcp:152700:5"/>with the Ladies) will be kindly received, as having been written on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for your divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to give me the occaſion of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick acknowledgement with what Profound Reſpect I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and most obedient Servant,
Prechac.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152700:5"/>
            <head>THE Heroine Muſqueteer: OR, THE FEMALE WARRIER.</head>
            <div type="parts">
               <p>
                  <hi>BEARN,</hi> though one of the leaſt Provinces ſubject to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> may be accounted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the moſt conſiderable, for the great number of Soldiers it ſends into the Armies. It hath the honour of giving Birth to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Prince, <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, and the Priviledges he granted it are ſufficient proof of the eſteem he had for the Inhabitants. And thoſe who now ſerve the King in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152700:6"/>his Wars, have made it appear they have not degenerated from the vertues of their Anceſtors. Beſides, as if it were not enough for this Province to produce Heroes in an Age, when all parts of <hi>France</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſuch plenty of them, it hath ſignaliz'd it ſelf in giving Birth to a Heroine, who ſeems to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the infirmities of her Sex, to aſſume the vigour and generoſity of the Maſculine, without loſing the beauty and ſweetneſs of her own, and to compoſe of both, the moſt perfect Perſon in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe.</p>
               <p>Her Name is <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Baron of <hi>Meyrac,</hi> one of the moſt Eminent of the Province, though leſs known at Court than in his Countrey, where he ſpent all his days. He had an only Son brought up at the Colledge of <hi>Pau</hi> whom he deſign'd to ſend timely to <hi>Paris</hi> to learn his Exerciſes, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152700:6"/>to fit him for the King's ſervice, in the Armies where he intended to provide him employment. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> was bred at home with her Parents as their darling: ſhe natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had that ſtrong inclination for Arms, ſhe knew ſooner how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a Gun, than to handle a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaff; and at nine years old could handle and uſe all ſorts of Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arms with incredible dexterity. She was extremely averſe from Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to read, and to perſwade her now and then to look on a Book, they were oblig'd to permit her to go a-hunting twice a week; but to purchaſe a pound of Powder ſhe would do any thing, how difficult ſoever. This for a time was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement to her Parents; till <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having one day ſhot at Pidgeons in a Barn full of Corn, it unfortunately took fire, which conſum'd a great part of it, though a great many hands were preſently
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152700:7"/>at work to quench it. At this, the Baron was ſo offended with his Daughter, that he would not ſee her for many days, nor pardon her, but upon condition ſhe would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver handle a Gun. Poor <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was very glad to be re-admitted upon any terms into the favour of a Father, ſo ſevere as ſhe knew hers to be: but that way of living be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quite againſt her temper, a week was ſcarce paſt, but there appear'd a viſible alteration in her looks. This alarm'd her Mother, who tenderly lov'd her, and having often, but in vain, endeavour'd to prevail with her Husband in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his Daughter, to remit a little of the rigour of his orders; ſhe order'd a Gun to be carried to a Neighbour's, where <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> by agreement with her Mother, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reſorted: And not daring to go a-Hunting, leſt the Father ſhould know it, ſhe ſhot at a mark
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152700:7"/>for her exerciſe. This reſtraint but heightned her paſſion for Hunting and Shooting, as ſhe made ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently appear by the advantages ſhe took of her Father's abſence, in a Journey about that time.</p>
               <p>The Baron in the Vacations ſent for his Son home; and Hunting being the principal Recreation of Countrey-Gentlemen, ſcarce a day paſt, but his Son made a match with his Friends for that ſport: He never went forth, but <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was cruelly vext, ſhe could not make one of the Game; and when he return'd, ſhe was not leſs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for the pleaſure ſhe fancied he had enjoy'd, and ſhe was unjuſtly debarr'd from, and ſeeing her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come every day home laden with Game that he had taken, ſhe could not forbear tormenting her ſelf for fear he would leave none for her.</p>
               <p>One day, as the Baron and his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152700:8"/>Son were a-Hunting, a Farmer came to the Caſtle to make his complaint of the great ſpoil done in his Corn by a wild Boar, and to beg aſſiſtance for killing him. The Baroneſs being aſſur'd the Boar ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail'd coming to the Corn in the Twilight, promis'd to take order in it, and diſmiſt the Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having over-heard the diſcourſe, ſaid not a word to her Mother, leſt ſhe might endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to divert her from her deſign; but charg'd her Gun with two bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and as it began to be dark, went away to the place the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-Man had ſpoken of; and to make the ſurer work, got up into a Tree a little diſtant from the Corn, with a reſolution to wait there the coming of the Boar. The ſame Countrey-man having met the Baron's Son as he return'd from Hunting, told him the ſtory, who loth to loſe ſo fair an occaſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152700:8"/>turn'd back into the Field, and fearing he was come too late, ſtole gently a croſs the Corn, and attended the Boar's coming near half an hour: But growing impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of longer ſtay, he reſolv'd to retire. His Siſter in the Tree, not well able to diſcern what ſhe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd ſhe ſaw, the Corn being high and night come on, made no doubt but it was the Boar ſtirring up and down; and to loſe no time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd her Gun, and kill'd her Brother. As he fell he cry'd out for help, which ſo troubled the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> that ſhe preſently fell down from the top of the Tree. The Countrey-man running in at the noiſe of the Gun, immediately met <hi>Chriſtina</hi> tearing her ſelf like a Woman diſtracted, and thought the Boar had wounded her: He ask'd her ſeveral queſtions, which ſhe anſwer'd not, but he took her up, and help'd her to walk a few
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152700:9"/>ſteps. When ſhe found her ſelf in a condition to go alone, ſhe order'd him to make all the haſte in his power to let the Baron know his Son lay a-dying, having been dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly wounded by the Boar; with that ſhe made away as faſt as ſhe could poſſibly, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whither to betake her ſelf. Having travell'd above an hour ſhe found her ſelf near a Caſtle belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Abbot <hi>Dizeſte,</hi> who was extremely ſurprized to ſee her ſo bloated with crying, and at that time of the night. But <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> having given him as good an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her misfortune as ſhe could in the caſe ſhe was in, the Abbot who was her Fathers very near Kinſman, inſtantly got on Horſe-back, and arriv'd at the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, the very moment they brought in the body of the poor Gentleman, who having loſt much blood for want of help, dy'd in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152700:9"/>Arms of the Chirurgeon who firſt dreſt him. All things in the Caſtle were in ſuch a confuſion, the Abbot could not learn the truth of the accident. The people would needs believe the Boar had kill'd the Gentleman, though they found two bullets in his body: But the Baron and his Lady, not finding <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> made no doubt but it was her act; and though they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd ſhe had don't by misfortune, the Baron was ſo tranſported with paſſion, for the loſs of his Son, that he made ſearch for his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all over the Town, with his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol in his hand, to ſacrifice her to his Wrath. The Abbot being told of it, ran after him, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid to him all that might be expected on ſuch an occaſion, he brought him back to the Caſtle, where he made uſe of many tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſcourſes to comfort him, but all to no purpoſe. Two Capuchins
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152700:10"/>came in at the noiſe of the diſaſter; and the Abbot having left them the care of comforting of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, return'd home to bring <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> the news of her Brother's Death, and the danger ſhe was in, if her Father ſhould diſcover where ſhe was; yet he aſſured her of his protection, and that he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake her.</p>
               <p>Returning two days after to <hi>Mey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rac,</hi> he was not a little ſurpriz'd to find the Capuchins exhortations had not abated in the leaſt the grief of the Baron, nor diminiſh'd his anger, but that he perſiſted in his reſolution to be the death of his Daughter, and would not admit of his Wife into his preſence, becauſe ſhe had been prevailed upon to ſpeak to him a word or two, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the unfortunate <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> This oblig'd the Abbot to hold a conference with two or three Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men more of the Barons, and to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152700:10"/>debate the buſineſs with them, and find out ſome means to ſave her from her Father's reſentment. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long diſcourſe, it was agreed ſhe ſhould be ſent into <hi>Spain;</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon</hi> being not above nine or ten Leagues from <hi>Bearn,</hi> and the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot having a Brother ſettled at <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragoſa</hi> many years, he was intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bear her company thither, and recommend her to his Brother, which he readily promis'd. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> troubled as ſhe was, receiv'd with joy the reſult of this confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and put her ſelf in a poſture to be gone on the morrow, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to order: but the Abbot ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reflected in the night on the conſequences of the intended Journey, found in it ſo many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, that he had almoſt alter'd his reſolution by morning. He fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw the beauty of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> would make a great noiſe in a ſtrange Countrey, being at twelve years old
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152700:11"/>far taller and handſomer than Maids of that Age ordinarily are, and eſpecially in <hi>Spain,</hi> where the Women are generally very low: beſides, he apprehended the frank humour of his Kinſ-woman, and the inclinations ſhe had ſo different from the reſt of her Sex, would hardly ever agree with the Genius of a Nation, where Women are oblig'd to live with a great deal of circumſpection, and that it might prove very troubleſome to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But the buſineſs was urgent, and he muſt reſolve: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> perceiving him waver, ask'd him the reaſon; he acquainted her with the difficulties he apprehended, and added, it was not decent or fit a young Maid ſhould run rambling into a ſtrange Countrey. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> longing to get out of her Father's reach, whom ſhe fear'd, and having a paſſionate deſire to ſee <hi>Spain,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Abbot, that if he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152700:11"/>would give her leave, ſhe would put on Boys Cloathes: And that ſhe might have a plauſible pretence for ſtaying in <hi>Spain,</hi> he need no more but tell his Brother he brought him a young Kinſman to learn <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and ſtudy ſome Months in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Saragoſa.</hi> The Abbot at firſt boggled at the propoſal as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous and childiſh. But find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her perſiſt in it, and promiſing ſhe would ſo diſguiſe her ſelf, they ſhould never diſcover her Sex, he was perſwaded by her. And hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſed her to be privately put into a habit ſuitable to her inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he thought ſhe became it ſo well, that he made no more ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but parted the next day with her for <hi>Saragoſa.</hi> Being arrived there, they were receiv'd by his Brother with incredible joy and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of thanks, that he would truſt him with the Education of a Kinſman of ſo promiſing a meen.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152700:12"/>The Abbot returned, and Don <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo</hi> his Brother, took pleaſure in making proviſion of neceſſaries for his young Kinſman. Schollars in <hi>Spain</hi> wear long, looſe, black Veſts like the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> a Habit that ſerved very well to make <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> look taller and handſomer, and her Hair being of a delicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brown, and cut after the <hi>Spaniſh</hi>-mode, had an admirable effect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the beholders. She no ſooner appear'd in the Univerſity, but ſhe drew after her the Eyes and the Hearts of the Students. It is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible what an advantage this was to the <hi>French</hi> Nation; for <hi>Spain</hi> being a Countrey inconvenient for Travellers, few Perſons of Quality go thither. And they ſeldom have amongſt them any <hi>French,</hi> unleſs it be ſome poor Labourers of the Mountains of <hi>Auvergne, Limoſin,</hi> and <hi>Bigorre,</hi> who for very ſmall wages do all manner of Drudgery. And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152700:12"/>the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who are naturally lazy, are willing to imploy <hi>French</hi>-men who ſerve them for money. This is the reaſon the People of thoſe Countreys, who ſeldom travel abroad, ſlight the <hi>French</hi> as they do, judging of the whole Nation by thoſe they ſee amongſt them. This general prejudice heightened their aſtoniſhment, who admir'd the beauty of <hi>Christina,</hi> and call'd her <hi>The Handſom Frenchman.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſtrove to be acquainted with the Stranger; and her Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was in a ſhort time ſo well ſettled at <hi>Saragoſa,</hi> that thoſe of the beſt Quality there order'd their Children, to get acquaintance with the young <hi>Frenchman,</hi> and to make him their Friend.</p>
               <p>The Marqueſs <hi>d'Oſſeyra</hi> then a Student there, went every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take him with him in his Coach to the Univerſity, and Don <hi>Philip de Palafox,</hi> Sonto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152700:13"/>
                  <hi>d'Arizza,</hi> brought him back for the moſt part in his. He viſited theſe two young Lords oftner than any other, eſpecially the Marqueſs <hi>d'Oſſeyra,</hi> who took pleaſure to teach him <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and tell him when he ſpoke amiſs. This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman had a Siſter married to the Marqueſs <hi>d'Aytona;</hi> who having heard an excellent Report of the handſome <hi>Frenchman,</hi> deſired her Brother to bring him with him to her Houſe, propoſing to her ſelf the pleaſure to be expected from the Converſation of two young Lads of their Age. But ſhe found it more charming, and was ſo ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the firſt Viſit, that ſhe pray'd her Brother to bring him often to her; being extremly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to ſee him and hear him ſpeak. To engage him to come again, ſhe preſented him with a Sword, and her Brother with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; which they carried com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152700:13"/>under their Gowns, as the Schollars in <hi>Spain</hi> uſually do. This Preſent was fatal to them both: For as they were going homewards one Evening very late, they met other Schollars who knew the <hi>Handſom-Frenchman,</hi> and could not forbear (out of a Natural-antipathy againſt the <hi>French</hi>) to give him ill-language and call him <hi>French-bougre.</hi> The Marqueſs <hi>d'Oſſeyra,</hi> thinking himſelf concern'd in their ill-uſage and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civility, and not daunted with the number of his Enemies, charged them vigorouſly with his Sword in his hand. The <hi>Handſom-Frenchman</hi> ſeconded him ſo well, that they two beat back five Men above thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty paces; till putting on too far, they were at laſt forc'd to give Ground, oppreſt with numbers of freſh aſſailants. The Marqueſs had a ſlight wound on the Face; and the <hi>Handſom-Frenchman</hi> receiv'd a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152700:14"/>went ſometimes with him to the Comedies and Opera's: About that time was preſented the Opera of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> and took very much; <hi>D'Angoſſe</hi> made uſe of the occaſion to take Places for S. <hi>Aubin</hi> and himſelf, in a Box, over-night. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving receiv'd his Ticket, he ſent the Ducheſs word of it, and advis'd her and the Marchioneſs to take Places in the Box right againſt them, to have the better view of S. <hi>Aubin;</hi> which was done accordingly. <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having taken their Places, the two Ladies little minded the Opera, being wholly taken up with viewing S. <hi>Aubin.</hi> Having taken exact notice of him, they thought they were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd this time; yet the Ducheſs, who could ſcarce believe a Maid ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to run through ſo many Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, would be better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd. She ſent for a Lacquey, who was a witty Fellow; and having
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152700:14"/>ſhew'd him S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> bid him put off his Livery, and having put on another Coat, follow that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man when he went out of the Play-houſe; but be ſure to do it ſo cloſely that ſhe might have a certain account where he lodg'd. The Lacquey perform'd, and gave his Miſtreſs an account. She and the Marchioneſs reſolv'd on a Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to try if S. <hi>Aubin</hi> were in truth the <hi>Heroine Muſqueteer,</hi> as they were made believe: After ſeveral Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients, propos'd and rejected, they pitch'd upon ſending him a Billet that Evening, which was to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whoever you are, you are a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Gentleman. I never ſaw you but once at the Opera, and you force me to a confeſſion which the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt Gentlemen of</hi> France <hi>have, by long ſervice and great aſſiduity, in vain endeavour'd to draw from me: I love you, Sir, and am aſham'd to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152700:15"/>let you know it, yet pleas'd with the thought of it. How great ſoever you are you muſt expect no more. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a quarter of an hours diſcourſe with you: my Quality debars me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining a ſtranger in Publick: follow this Lacquey, he will bring you to a ſight of me. If afterwards you think me worthy the eſteem and addreſſes of a Man of Honour, I dare not paſs my word, but Time and your good Meen may triumph over my weakneſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>They read the Billet ſeveral times over: The Ducheſs thought it too free, and would have burnt it; but the Marchioneſs told her it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd not, being written to a Maid, and by an unknown hand. The Ducheſs, ſway'd with theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, call'd for the Lacquey; and having inſtructed him what to do, gave him ſtrict charge of the Billet. The Lacquey being come to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152700:15"/>Houſe where S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, went to his Apartment and deliver'd him the Billet; which he read, and was not a little ſurpriz'd. Having read it, he was very much perplex'd, having a thouſand thoughts in his head, not knowing what courſe to take: He was fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of engaging in an affair might be difficult to get rid of: On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, he knew that a Lady of Quality, if ſlighted, is a dangerous Enemy: This, and his natural Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, made him deſire the Ladies acquaintance. He read the Billet over again, and feeing nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd but what he thought might be granted, and judging others as reſerv'd as himſelf, he reſolv'd to follow the Lacquey; and having wrapt up himſelf in a Cloak, bid the Boy lead the way. Probably the Reader may think a Maid ſcarce capable of ſuch a Reſolution; but he is to conſider our <hi>Heroine</hi> was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152700:16"/>naturally couragious and bold, yet as tender of her honour (in the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials) as the moſt reſerv'd. I have heard her ſay, ſhe thought her ſelf ſafer in Mans Habit, than that of her Sex; as expoſing her more to diſcourſe commonly us'd to Women, if tolerably handſome, which at length leaves an impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. About Eleven a Clock the Foot-Boy led him through a little Gate, of which he had the Key for the purpoſe; S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſtaid in a Cloſet while the Lacquey gave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it to the Dutcheſs, who was then with the Marchioneſs. It ſurpriz'd them to hear the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was come, as appointed; they began to repent their haſty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, fearing they ſhould meet with a ſecond Marqueſs <hi>de Meſples.</hi> The Ducheſs being a Lady of eminent Vertue, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd to preſerve her Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, was upon ſending him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152700:16"/>without ſeeing him; and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly had done it, but for fear of her Letter, which S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> if a Man, (as for ought ſhe knew he was) might make very ill uſe of: The deſire ſhe had to have it again in her hands, and her natural Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, made her reſolve to admit him entrance. The firſt Civilities being over, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> being alone with the two Ladies, who ey'd him very narrowly, appear'd ſo handſome that they believ'd him of their Sex. The Ducheſs, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to get her Billet into her hands, told him he might perhaps have a very ill opinion of a Lady who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd ſo forward, yet ſhe thought ſhe could not do too much to make ſure of ſo handſome a Gentleman: The Lady you ſee with me is my Confident, and we two fram'd the Billet I ſent you. I fear it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear too paſſionate, and being not ſo well acquainted with you as to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152700:17"/>leave in your hands a Paper of that freedom, I deſire you to reſtore it me: hereafter poſſibly I may know you ſo well, as to put my Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into your hands. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently took it out of his Pocket, and the Ducheſs receiving it threw it in the Fire: and changing her tone, I muſt confeſs Sir, ſays ſhe, my Curioſity hath expos'd me to a great deal of folly. We have read a Book, call'd <hi>The Heroine Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer,</hi> and had a deſire to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſo extraordinary a Perſon. We were aſſur'd ſhe was at <hi>Paris,</hi> and that you were inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with her: you will highly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to bring us acquainted with her. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was ſo aſtoniſh'd at the diſcourſe he had not a word to ſay. The Marchioneſs perceiving it, made uſe of that Moment for the tryal ſhe had unhappily made upon <hi>Meſples,</hi> and found whad ſhe look'd for: The Ladies embrac'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152700:17"/>our <hi>Heroine,</hi> and made her a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand obliging offers of their ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> aſham'd to ſee her ſelf diſcover'd, anſwer'd them with as much civility as the diſorder ſhe was in would permit. The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs conjur'd her to tell her ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely if all that was written of her was true. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> declar'd what was true, and what was of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors invention. The Ducheſs was ſo well ſatisfi'd with our <hi>Heroine's</hi> modeſty and diſcourſe, that ſhe preſs'd her very much to take a Chamber in her Houſe, aſſuring her ſhe ſhould be us'd as a Perſon of Quality and Merit. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd, and gave ſo good reaſons for it that the Ducheſs was ſatisfi'd, but pray'd her to viſit her as often as poſſible: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> promis'd it, and after a long diſcourſe, and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual promiſes of ſecrecy, retir'd. But for all their aſſurance of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Counſel, ſhe doubted their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152700:18"/>performance; and could not rely on their diſcretion without ſcruple and diffidence, which gave her no ſmall diſquiet.</p>
               <p>About this time S. <hi>Aubin</hi> receiv'd news from <hi>Bearn,</hi> that upon a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his death ſome of his Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred had poſſeſt themſelves of part of his Eſtate. The Abbot <hi>Dizett</hi> who had the management of his Affairs advis'd him to make a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Bearn,</hi> to diſſipate, by his preſence, the falſe reports of his death, and to take order for other matters. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> loth to go ſo far from the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra,</hi> and expecting, with impatience, the end of the Campaign in order to Marriage, choſe rather to hazard the loſs of his Eſtate, than engage in buſineſs that would rob him of thoſe precious Moments he thought better beſtow'd in thinking of his Love. Upon a ſecond Letter to the ſame purpoſe, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> deſir'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152700:18"/>
                  <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> to undertake the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he readily took the Charge of it, and ſet out for <hi>Bearn</hi> within two days.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Aubin</hi> reflecting on his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to viſit the Ducheſs, thought himſelf indiſpenſably o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to be as good as his word. He went to her, and was kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; there was commonly good Company there. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was treated in ſo obliging a manner, that every one took notice of it, and inquir'd who that young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was, and very few knew him. A Principal Lord of the Court had long been in Love with the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs and viſited her frequently, but found his addreſſes fruitleſs, and had no further advantage by them, than an opportunity to gain an intereſt in the Servants by his Liberality. He was not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd by the ſevere Vertue of the Ducheſs from ſeeing her often, in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152700:19"/>hopes to prevail with her at Long-run. The Count <hi>d' Ex</hi> (for ſo was the Gentleman call'd) was ſo far in Love that he eaſily became jealous, and could not with patience endure to ſee how familiarly the Ducheſs convers'd with this Stranger: He queſtion'd the Maids of his Party about it, but they could not give him a ſatisfactory account; the Lacqueys were as much to ſeek as the Maids. He whom the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs had employ'd to carry the Billet to S. <hi>Aubin</hi> being no more proof than others of his Coat to the temptations of Gain, and finding no advantage from being his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes Confident, would not ſlip the opportunity of getting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the Count on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. He told the Count of the Billet, and how he thought the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs became firſt engag'd with the Stranger, not forgetting the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage at the Opera. Here I cannot
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152700:19"/>forbear blaming the injuſtice of moſt Men, to be ſo eaſily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the ill Conduct of Women: How many are there who are very vertuous, yet have not eſcap'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condemn'd for debauch'd, upon the Report of a Maid-ſervant diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd, or a Foot boy miſ-inform'd? This Report paſſes to other Women, and ſeldom fails of coming to the Ears of one or other, who will be glad of the occaſion to ſpeak as ill of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as ſhe knows her ſelf to be deſervedly ſpoken of; and will be fure to divulge it very carefully, in hopes to confound the Criminal with the Innocent: The Story lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes nothing by the Carriage, every one adds ſomething to ſet it off the better; and there needs no more to deſtroy a Womans Reputation: Of which, I could give you ſeveral Inſtances.</p>
               <p>The Count was much ſurpriz'd at the diſcourſe of the Lacquey:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152700:20"/>He believ'd it without examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and his Jealouſie made him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve much more: It fail'd not to repreſent to him, that a Stranger of Quality, perhaps as obſcure as his Name, was in favour with a Lady of her Merit and Rank, when ſhe ſlighted him who was inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to few in the Kingdom, for handſomneſs, Birth, or Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This made him reſolve to be reveng'd of his Miſtreſs, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving her of her Favorite. The Count, though otherwiſe very ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, was haſty of humour, and fiery: His Jealouſie requir'd him to make his Rival a Victim, which the goodneſs of his Nature would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſent to: It would have been no hard matter to ruine his Rival, but his revenge would not have been compleat, if ſome part of it fell not on his Miſtreſs. After much irreſolution, he pitch'd upon a fatisfaction no leſs cruel, than
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152700:20"/>gallant: He had a Domeſtick, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry witty and intelligent, to whom he diſcover'd his deſign, and told him he intended to truſt him with the execution; that his firſt care muſt be to find out a Wench who had been debauch'd through want of Money and Experience, and lik'd it ſo well that ſhe continued the Trade; that he could not fail of choice in ſo great a Town, and therefore muſt pick out the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt he could find, but ſhe muſt be ſuch as could do him a kindneſs he ſhould have cauſe to remember while he liv'd: And to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he was not to ſpare coſt or pains; but withall, to put her into excellent Habit, lodge her in the beſt Apartment of the Houſe, and inſtruct her how to counterfeit, in her deportment, a Lady of Quality. The Servant found a Perſon excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently qualifi'd for the ſervice his Maſter deſir'd from her, and ſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152700:21"/>that ſhe quickly learnt her Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. This was ſo well perform'd, that the Count, who had reſolv'd to have S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſtolen away, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the care of it to the ſame Servant; and took him along with him to the Ducheſs's to ſhew him S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> to prevent a miſtake. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> went commonly in a Chair, and uſually retir'd from the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs's at ten or eleven Clock at Night. The Count's Servant ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made the Chair-men drunk, got others to wait in their room: S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> at coming off from the Ducheſs, not finding his Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, made uſe of the next at hand. Three Men, well-arm'd, had order to guard the Chair: One of them, by the way, whiſpers S. <hi>Aubin</hi> in the Ear, that a Lady of Quality, being paſſionately in Love with him, had order'd them to ſteal him to her: adding, 'twas in vain to reſiſt, for they were able to force
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152700:21"/>him. St. <hi>Aubin,</hi> though ſurpriz'd at the Complement, was ſo us'd to extraordinary Adventures, that he permitted himſelf to be quietly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed where the pretended good Fortune waited him: As ſoon as he was arriv'd, two Men ſeiz'd him, and led him in the dark up a back ſtair; and having croſs'd two Apar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tments, thruſt him ſomewhat rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into a Chamber full of Lights, and nobly furniſht: One of them who brought him thither took care to ſhut the Door faſt enough. The Illuſtrious Perſonage, who was there ready to receive him, would not give him time to know her, but took him about the Neck with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of a paſſionate joy, as true as what is affected can be; you would have thought the rich Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ſhe was in had made her forget the meanneſs of her condition. S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> reſolv'd what to do, was not daunted at all, but anſwer'd her
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152700:22"/>paſſion with all the civility and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect imaginable: But theſe were not the Entertainment ſhe look'd for, and after long diſcourſe the fair Lady having in vain endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd by an affected modeſty to raiſe the Gentlemans Spirits, was quite tyr'd with his reſerv'dneſs, and attributing his want of bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the trouble he ſaid he was in at ſight of her; I come not, ſays ſhe, to give you trouble, but to receive Love from you: At this, ſhe hid her face with her Fan, as if ſhe had been aſham'd ſhe had let fall expreſſions ſo free. S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> who thought of nothing more than how to get well out of the Bryers, was in ſome hopes obſerving her modeſty, and aſſur'd her he had a great inclination to love her, that he was unworthy ſo much favour, but would make it his buſineſs to merit it by his ſervices: I will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with you in that point, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152700:22"/>ſhe, and, ſince I muſt tell you all, I deſire we may ſpend this night together: S. <hi>Aubin</hi> who could not believe what he had heard ſay of the impudence of ſome women, and expected not ſo very plain Engliſh, ſtood a while mute; And ſeeing no other courſe to take fell at her feet (whom he thought a perſon of Quality) and confeſſ'd ingenuouſly he was a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: The poor Wench who was made believe ſhe ſhould be largely rewarded, was in a lamentable fear to loſe what was promis'd her, if it were once known ſhe had not not done the ſervice expected from her: which troubl'd her the more, for that ſhe had deſign'd the money for ſeveral neceſſary uſes, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly for getting rid of that which made her ſo fit for the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of her paymaſter, ſhe then fell at S. <hi>Aubins</hi> feet, and told him word by word all the intrigue, advertiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152700:23"/>him the maſter of the houſe (whom ſhe knew not) was jealous of ſome perſon of quality. It was no hard Matter for S. <hi>Aubin</hi> to gueſs it was the Dutcheſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting with horror on the Regale provided for him, he made the Wench ſenſible it was their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt to keep mutual ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which was accordingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſ'd, and having agreed what to ſay; the Wench went to bed, which ſhe took care to tumble ſo as if two had lain there: S. <hi>Aubin</hi> lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtooles. And on the morrow a little before day the Wench went according to order to give, a boy who was in an antichamber hard by, notice of what paſt, aſſuring him he might when he pleaſ'd ſend away the Gallant who was ſo ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pepper'd ſhe undertook he ſhould never forget that nights work. The boygave his Maſter this account, and he was very well ſatisfied. He ſent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152700:23"/>the Wench word ſhe ſhould blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold her lover, and perſwade him to be led ſo into the place Royal, it being too early to get a Chair: and it might concern her how ſhe got ryd of him. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> well pleaſ'd to ſee an end of an adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had ſo terribly frightn'd him; forgot not to give her who had ſo faithfully ſerv'd him, ſome marks of his acknowledgment: His ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue prompted him to exhort her to live honeſtly, which he ſeconded with giving her ſome means to do it, he follow'd his guides, and aſſoon as he was at liberty went to his lodging to bed.</p>
               <p>When he had reſted ſufficiently he went to the Dutcheſs's aſſoon as he thought her in a condition to to be ſeen, and praid her to ſend one for the Marchioneſs, aſſuring her ſhe had news to tell them would make them very merry: Aſſoon as ſhe was come they lock'd themſelves
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152700:24"/>up in a room where S. <hi>Aubin</hi> told them the particulars of the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he had met with the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: The Dutcheſs, who very well knew the kindneſs the Count had for her, and was ſufficiently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his jealous humour, preſently ſuſpected he had the principal hand in it, which was confirm'd by the circumſtances, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> related. To put it out of doubt, they agree'd that S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſhould not for two days appear at the Dutcheſs's, and that when firſt the Count came thither, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs ſhould inſenſibly fall into diſcourſe of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> and the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs ſhould expreſs much ſorrow for his ſickneſs; which would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly produce a diſcovery of the Counts thoughts of the buſineſs. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> vaniſht, the Count came, as he was wont, to the Dutcheſs, and ſav'd the Marchioneſs the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the diſcourſe agreed on, by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152700:24"/>asking the Dutcheſs why ſhe look'd ſo ſad: The Marchioneſs anſwer'd that S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> whom the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs had a value for, was ſick, and that ſhe was troubl'd for want of his good company: the Count was ſo glad at the news that he could not forbear asking very merrily what he aild; the Marchioneſs, who knew the reaſon of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaid ſhe knew not, and proceeded no further.</p>
               <p>The Ducheſs, who liv'd very lovingly with her Husband, had told him the ſtory of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and how ſhe had got acquaintance with that maid in Mans Clothes: And being glad of an occaſion to make him merry, ſhe ſcrupl'd not to tell him the adventure of the Count, at which they laugh'd very heartily.</p>
               <p>It was a fine time for going into the Country: The Duke having a houſe within fifteen Leagues of <hi>Paris,</hi> was minded to ſpend ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152700:25"/>time there, and told his Wife ſhe would do him a pleaſure to bring ſome good company thither. The Marchioneſs being a very Jovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Lady promiſ'd to make one; they had a great deſire to have S. <hi>Aubin</hi> along with them, and the Duch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs had invited him two or three times but could not prevail: when he came to take his leave of theſe Ladies the day before their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Marchioneſs told him, if he would not go along with them ſhe would diſcover the ſecret of his ſex. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was loth to go far from <hi>Paris</hi> for fear of expoſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (as tis ſaid) to new adventures, though it was for another reaſon; yet he was ſo mov'd with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs's threats that he reſolv'd to go along: the Duke was very glad, and they promiſ'd all to keep S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> Councell. When they were got into the Country the Ladies thought of nothing but their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152700:25"/>Hunting, Gameing, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and making good cheer took up their time: The Dutcheſs having conſider'd that the Count continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his miſtake, and ſtill thought her Criminal, was troubled ſhe had not undeceiv'd him, ſhe ſpoke of it to her Husband who thought ſhe had reaſon, it being ever to a Ladies diſadvantage to give any cauſe of ſuſpecting her Conduct. They reſolv'd the Duke ſhould write him a Letter to invite him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Country: The Count who thought very ill of that Journey the Ducheſs had taken, though he did not know S. <hi>Aubin</hi> went with her, was glad the Duke had given him the occaſion of viſiting them, and imagin'd the Duke had written without acquainting his Ducheſs. He got thither within two days, and was ſurpriz'd to find ſo good company; there care was taken at his firſt arrival to have S. <hi>Aubin</hi> out
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152700:26"/>of the way. After Supper the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs ſaid, ſhe had lighted that day on the pleaſanteſt ſtory in the World: they pray'd her to acquaint the company with it; ſhe excuſ'd her ſelf ſaying, ſhe had a very ill memory: with that, ſhe ſtept a little from the table, and taking a book out of her pocket where ſhe had writ what ſhe had to ſay, ſhe pretended to make uſe of it to help her memory, and ſaid that a perſon of quality had been jealous of a Maid in Mans Clothes, and ſo went ongiving an exact and particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all that happend to S. <hi>Aubin</hi> at the Counts, and how he had been deceiv'd when he thought himſelf reveng'd: the Duke and his Ducheſs the mean while obſerv'd the Count, who knowing himſelf by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to be the party intended, chang'd colour and countenance at every word: The Marchioneſs hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a ſtop at the feigned ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152700:26"/>of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> the Ducheſs was earneſt to know if the Count had been diſabus'd: The Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs takes her Book in hand, and read that; the Lady principally concern'd, went ſhortly after into the Countrey, and having ſcrupl'd the leaving the Count in a miſtake ſo diſadvantageous to her, had prai'd her Husband to invite the Count to come and viſit them. But how did ſhe juſtify her ſelf, ſays the Ducheſs, my Book ſays no more replyes the Marchioneſs. This Gentleman, the Count being newly arriv'd from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> may probably inform you. Never was Man more out of Countenance then he: The Duke pittying the Diſorder he was in, told him S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was, <hi>The Heroine Muſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teer;</hi> the Count begg'd the Duch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs pardon, giving her many ſorry reaſons to juſtify himſelf, which ſhe little valued: They ſent for S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having firſt ingag'd the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152700:27"/>Count not to diſcover the ſecret: they had good laughing at the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture; but the Count was ſo confounded at it that he durſt no more ſpeak to the Ducheſs, and ſhortly after return'd to <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Aubin</hi> in the mean time was not ſo merry as formerly, the ſame reaſon that ſtopt his Journey to <hi>Bearn</hi> would not permit him to be long abſent from <hi>Paris</hi> with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: He expected news from the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra,</hi> but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd not any, though they had taken care to agree a way to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Correſpondence. As he was walking one day with the Ducheſs, he ſpi'd three <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldiers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning home-wards from <hi>Flanders,</hi> he ſpoke to them in Spaniſh and ask'd them a hundred queſtions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra:</hi> One of the Souldiers hearing him repeat ſo often the Marqueſs's name, ask'd him boldly if he knew him,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152700:27"/>and had any concern with him. I have been his priſoner, ſays S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> and he uſ'd me ſo well I ſhall acknowledge it while I live: The Ducheſs perceiving by S. <hi>Aubins</hi> countenance how glad he was to diſcourſe with the ſtrangers, was willing to give him time enough to do it at his leiſure, and order'd one of her Servants to entertain them that day, and take care of them: They were ſcarce got into the Houſe, but S. <hi>Aubin</hi> found them out, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing himſelf to the Souldier, who ſeem'd beſt acquainted with the Marqueſs, he ask'd a Thouſand particulars concerning him. The Souldier aſtoniſht to find a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo acknowledging, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him the Marqueſs's very good friend, confeſſ'd he was his domeſtick, and had by the way met with thoſe two Souldiers going for <hi>Spain:</hi> But as for him he went nofur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>Paris,</hi> on buſineſs from his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152700:28"/>Maſter: S. <hi>Aubin</hi> Raviſhed at the newes, and thinking himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Journey, ask'd if he had not Letters for <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> The <hi>Spaniard</hi> aſtoniſht to find him ſo wellacquainted with the Marqueſs's affairs, told him he had ſeveral for her; give 'em me then ſays <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> forgetting her ſelf to be S. <hi>Aubin.</hi> The <hi>Spaniard</hi> look'd attentively on him, and with the cool gravity uſual in thoſe of his Nation, anſwered he would rather part with his life: I am <hi>Chriſtinas</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and a good friend of your Maſters, ſays S. <hi>Aubin.</hi> And you may truſt me with them: but the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was not to be perſwaded out of them. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſeeing it and being impatient to have a ſight of Letters ſhe ſo dearly long'd for, confeſſ'd ſhe was <hi>Chriſtina</hi> and had that day diſguiſed her ſelf into Mans habit for hunting: Old birds are not caught with chaff,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152700:28"/>ſays the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> I'll as ſoon part with my life as my Letters, which he bound with two or three Spaniſh oaths, and quitting S. <hi>Aubin</hi> went ſtrait to his Comrads and ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward immediately for <hi>Paris:</hi> S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was upon the point of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them to ſet upon them by the way, and force the Letters from them; but fearing the Conſequence of an action ſo raſh in a Kingdome where ſuch violence is not allow'd, he pray'd the Ducheſs to give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for horſes to carry him preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Paris,</hi> fearing if the <hi>Spaniard</hi> miſt of him there, he would return preſently for <hi>Flanders.</hi> The Duch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs not knowing the reaſon of this haſte, endeavour'd very civilly to engage him to longer ſtay. S. <hi>Anbin</hi> vext at her unſeaſonable ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility acquainted her with what had paſt between him and the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> The Dutcheſs in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to a Lovers impatience ſent
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152700:29"/>horſes the ſame day to wait S. <hi>Aubins</hi> coming by the way, who on the morrow went off in her Coach, and in a ſhort time arrriv'd at <hi>Paris.</hi> He fail'd not to go to the place where he knew the Marqueſs would addreſs his Letters, and thought it requiſite to put on wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans habit, leſt the incredulous <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſhould ſcruple delivering him the packet: ſoon after the <hi>Spaniard</hi> arriv'd, and having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd to ſpeak with <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> he deliver'd the Letters, applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf much that he had not truſted them with a young Gentleman who would have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd him with untruths: But he had miſtaken his mark, for he could have rather parted with his life than his Letters: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> more intent about reading her Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters than hearing his bravadoes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd ſeveral which pleaſed her well: I would have inſerted them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152700:29"/>here for the Readers ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but there are a ſort of Letters very good for the writer and for the party they are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to, but flat and inſipid to others who have not the key to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the meaning and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the delicacy of them: I ſhall only give you one I thought eaſieſt to be underſtood.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Attribute my ſilence to the Exceſs of my Love: when my letters are written I look upon them as yours, which makes them ſo dear to me That I cannot find in my heart to expoſe them to the danger of falling into the hands of ſtrangers. By all thoſe I ſend you by the expreſs, you will find you wholly take up my thoughts. It is an age ſince the beginning of this Campagne: why ſhould the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary progreſs of our armyes ſtop that of my Love. If poſſible draw near one of the conquer'd Towns that I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152700:30"/>may have the pleaſure at laſt to think I am not far from you, and that if we lay a ſiege, as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is, I may flatter my ſelf with the hopes of having you my priſoner: But for Heavens ſake, be not in the place, for I foreſee the Cannon will be ill ſerv'd when I think it may be diſcharg'd againſt you. And I would chooſe rather to loſe my office than do it on ſuch an occaſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> in Reading the ſeveral Leters had all the joy a perſon in love is capable of after long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of news from her Lover.</p>
               <p>This was her Anſwer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I am very well pleaſ'd with your Letters: they are all very paſſionate. But you alarm me in telling me you are going to form a ſiege. I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for you that the ſucceſs will not anſwer your hopes: Let me intreat you to think of nothing but loving me,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152700:30"/>there you are ſure of Conqueſt, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is uncertain. I will draw to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Frontiers, becauſe you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it; I know I ſhall be better at eaſe, and I take pleaſure before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand to think I ſhall hear from you oftner: Make an end of this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pain as ſoon as you can, Love will make you amends for the damage your glory ſuffers by it.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſent back the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs's Man with this anſwer, and reſum'd her Mans Habit, and the Name of S. <hi>Aubin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> in the mean time was return'd from <hi>Bearn,</hi> and had, with the help of the Abbot <hi>d' Izette,</hi> happily ended what he had to do there on S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s account, and much to his advantage; for which <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> expected no ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment. He could not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine but <hi>Chriſtina</hi> would at length be ſenſible of his affection
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152700:31"/>for her: And when S. <hi>Aubin</hi> would have made him a conſiderable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, proportionable to the ſervice he had done him, <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> took it for an affront, and told <hi>Chriſtina</hi> he thought himſelf not unworthy of her affection. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was ſo well acquainted with the boldneſs natural to thoſe of his Country, that it ſurpriz'd him not at all: But to undeceive him, once for all, told <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> he had a very high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and value for him, and would evidence it on all occaſions; but intreated him for the future to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his thoughts better, than to give him occaſion to forbear his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and forbid him further Viſits; which he would infallibly do, if he continued to diſcourſe him at that bold rate. <hi>D' Angoſſe</hi> was too much a <hi>Gaſcon</hi> to be diſcourag'd at this, ſo that S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> to be rid of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome importunities, was forc'd to change his Lodging.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152700:31"/>
               <p>There was about this time, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that the Confederate Army had inveſted <hi>Charleroy,</hi> and begun already to form the Siege: Moſt of the young Gentlemen at Court, and other Volunteers, left <hi>Paris</hi> upon the news, and went for the <hi>French</hi> Army, not doubting but the Marſhal <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it, would attack the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in their Lines. The Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd extremely in two or three days, Volunteers coming in Poſt from all Parts, and not finding Horſes on the great Roads, ſome were forc'd to take by-ways to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh themſelves, that they might come in time. The Marqueſs <hi>de Fervaques,</hi> willing to be there with the firſt, to ſignalize himſelf on this, and other occaſions, had the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune to be taken by the way, by a Party of the Enemies. The Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer who Commanded the Party, having ſeiz'd ſome Books among
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152700:32"/>Monſieur <hi>Fervaques</hi>'s Baggage, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd one, which prov'd the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roine Muſqueteer:</hi> the Title made him eager to read it. This Officer had been bred Page to the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra,</hi> and not a little ſurpriz'd to find the Marqueſs's Name ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Book, he ſent it the Marqueſs, who was extremely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſht at it.</p>
               <p>While every one wondred at the Confederates Reſolution to lay Siege to <hi>Charleroy,</hi> having former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attempted it in vain. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> allarm'd to hear the expedition ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally cry'd down as raſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advis'd, and all <hi>France</hi> confident it would come to nothing, began to be afraid for the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra.</hi> He had not the patience to wait information, by the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick News, what was become of the Marqueſs; but puſh'd on by a love, to which no difficulty was inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, rid Poſt to <hi>Charleroy,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152700:32"/>the cauſe of his Journey to be only a deſire of honour, natural to the <hi>French</hi> Gentry: Every Horſe-man he met by the way he fancy'd might me a Courrier to carry news of the defeat of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. But when he came to the Army, he found the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates had been ſo wiſe to ſave him the fright his Love might have put him to for danger to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs. They had, upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the King's Army, rais'd the Siege, as the beſt of their Game. The Confederates having made a very good Retreat, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſaw there was no cauſe of further fear on their account, the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> being ſafe; but he could not find in his heart to return for <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> without giving the Marqueſs notice: He was ſo pleas'd with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo near the Man he lov'd beſt of any living, that he reſolv'd to ſtay in <hi>Flanders:</hi> And having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152700:33"/>himſelf in the beginning of the Campain to ſpend ſome time at <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> at <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he took that occaſion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue nearer the Marqueſs: And conſidering it would be difficult hearing from him at <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> where Count <hi>Magalotti</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor was very ſtrict to prevent intelligence with the Enemy, he made ſure before-hand of a <hi>Ligeois</hi> Lad, who under pretence of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Victuals, went indifferently to both Armies; and was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> as well as <hi>French</hi> Towns. The <hi>Ligeois</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promis'd to ſerve him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, he went into <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> and ſent the Boy into the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army with this Letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Your Enterprize of</hi> Charleroy <hi>put me in ſuch a fright, that I could not wait the ſucceſs in quiet: How could I be at reſt, when I was to expect
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152700:33"/>every hour deſigns againſt you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Where-ever I went, judge what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I was in, who could not wiſh the glory of my Country, without giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an allarm to my Love; nor pray for your proſperity, without breach of my allegiance: Make me a-mends for the trouble you have caus'd me, by letting me hear often from you at</hi> Valenciennes, <hi>where I reſolve to ſtay and ſee what will become of you.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>When the <hi>Ligeois</hi> came to the Confederate Army to deliver the Letter, he found all in diſorder there, by miſ-underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Generals; one blaming the other for the miſcarriage of the buſineſs of <hi>Charleroy.</hi> He was told the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were withdrawn and that the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra,</hi> Commanded a Body a-part about <hi>Ghent:</hi> The <hi>Ligeois</hi> found him there, and having deliver'd the Letter, the Marqueſs rewarded
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152700:34"/>him ſo, that he had cauſe to wiſh he might have more ſuch Letters to carry, and ſoon after ſent him back with this Anſwer.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I am extremely oblig'd to you for the fright you were in, though it be the greateſt harm our Army hath done. We are ſo us'd to ill ſucceſs, we are not at all mov'd at it: yet I ſhould be he artily ſorry for it, but that I am perſwaded you make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between me and others; and believe did I act a part, I would allarm you oftner. But why ſhould our Billets ſtill ſpeak of War, which ought to be full of ſweetneſs and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs? Do you know, our buſineſs is grown Publick, and that there's a Book Printed, Intituled</hi> The Heroine Muſqueteer? <hi>Since we are made the Subject of Romances, let's make an end as ſoon as we can, and enjoy the fruits of our Love, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the Publick any longer at our coſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:152700:34"/>
               <p>This Letter was delivered S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> at <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> where he was receiv'd by <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Parents with Demonſtrations of very great joy, and Evidences of a ſincere kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. They flatter'd themſelves ſtill with the hopes of having him their Son-in-Law; and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in this opinion, by his return, they made him very welcom, and gave him the beſt entertainment they could. Only <hi>Mariana</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd troubled at the ſight of S. <hi>Aubin:</hi> An <hi>Italian</hi> Captain in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galottes</hi>'s Regiment, had, by his ſubtil inſinuations, got that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage over the ſimplicity of the honeſt <hi>Hemyn,</hi> that ſhe told him all that had paſs'd between her and S. <hi>Aubin;</hi> and the deſign of her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to make her his Wife, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his great indifference for her. The <hi>Italian</hi> pretending himſelf very much concern'd for her, us'd all his endeavours to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152700:35"/>her thoughts of that chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericall Marriage, aſſuring her, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> who apparently was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of quality, had no thoughts of marrying her, having not as much as writ her a line ſince he left her: I know, adds he, the French well enough, they engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with women only for diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, Ambition and the thirſt of Glory are their predominant paſſion: But, 'tis no ſmall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to a fair Lady ſo lovely as you are, to be expos'd to the ſlights of a preſumtuous youngſter, who perhaps makes ſport in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey with the obliging offers your parents have made him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mariana</hi> having been frequently diſcourag'd thus, found it no hard matter to forget S. <hi>Aubin:</hi> And the Captain finding her ſo well diſpoſ'd, fail'd not to offer her his ſervice; and to make her ſenſible of the great deſire he had to merit
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152700:35"/>her good opinion. Tis no wonder a young maid who fanci'd all Men as ſhy as S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> ſhould be tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en at laſt with the aſſiduity of a ſmooth tongu'd, and cunning <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> Love, that you may be lov'd is a maxime ſeldom fails, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were that the Captain was in love with <hi>Mariana,</hi> or pretend'd it only, ſhe was quickly comforted for the abſence of S. <hi>Aubin</hi> by the care this <hi>Italian</hi> took to entertain her with frequent diſcourſes of the paſſion he had for her, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference of S. <hi>Aubin:</hi> when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to <hi>Valenciennes</hi> ſhe had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of her affection, and all her Parents cares to the <hi>Frenchman</hi> were but ſo many pieces of morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to <hi>Mariana,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of them to the Captain. But when ſhe reflected on her ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to him, and the pleaſure of being beholding to ſo handſome a Gentleman, her ſenſe of grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152700:36"/>could not but reproach her for loving another. She acquainted the <hi>Italian</hi> with her reflections, who alarm'd at the diſcourſe, made uſe of all the intereſt his ſuttleties had gain'd in the credulous Girl: And conſidering he might never have ſo good an opportunity for making his fortune, he was ſo fearful S. <hi>Aubins</hi> preſence might revive <hi>Marianas</hi> former inclinations, and ſo loth to loſe what he thought himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt maſter of, that he made uſe of ſuch means to make ſure of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana,</hi> it was not in her parents pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to diſpoſe of her to another. He forgot neither promiſe nor oath, and preſſ'd her ſo hard that ſhe thought it but reaſonable togrant him the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt favours his love could expect: her mother reproach'd her for enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Captain ſo conſtantly and ſlighting S. <hi>Aubin.</hi> But her Mothers diſcourſe and S. <hi>Aubins</hi> cold civilities were merely thrown away upon her, who had receiv'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152700:36"/>ſuch effectual proof of the Captains kindneſs: S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was ſo taken up with writing Letters to the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra,</hi> and ſo pleas'd with reading his anſwers, that 'tis no wonder he concern'd not himſelf much with other peoples buſineſs. <hi>Mariana</hi> having improv'd her wit by converſing with the <hi>Italian,</hi> advis'd him to get ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> as an infallible means to be welcome to her parents, by reaſon of the eſteem and kindneſs they had for that <hi>Frenchman.</hi> Another man would have ſcrupl'd ſeeing a Rival ſo dangerous as S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> but an <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> hath an abſolute command of his paſſion: The Captain diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the hatred he had for S. <hi>Aubin</hi> on <hi>marianas</hi> account, did him all the civilities imaginable, of which the <hi>Italians</hi> never are Niggards; S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> as courteouſly return'd them. The ouning <hi>Italian</hi> eaſily had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> that in a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152700:37"/>ſhort time they were intimate Friends: and the Captain to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover S. <hi>Aubins</hi> deſigns upon <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana</hi> frequently made her the ſubject of their diſcourſe. S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> frankly declar'd he had an eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eem for her, The Captain willing to try him further, and know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he lov'd her, repli'd cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly that few are ſatisfi'd with a bare eſteem of a young Lady of <hi>Mariana's</hi> qualities: I can go no further, ſays S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to diſabuſe her parents; and ſhould be very ſorry they ſhould for hopes which can never take effect, let ſlip the opportunities of ſetling their daughter. The <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> well ſatisfi'd with an anſwer ſo agreeable to his deſires, concluded from S. <hi>Aubins</hi> diſcourſe he was very well born, and thought not of matching into an inferior family, which made him ever after make his Court to S. <hi>Aubin</hi> with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary deference.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:152700:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marianas</hi> Father was every day more and more charm'd with S. <hi>Aubin's</hi> behaviour and carriage, and heartily ſorry to ſee him ſo little concern'd for his daughter. The <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> frequented the houſe under pretence of ſeeing S. <hi>Aubin. Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's</hi> Father taking him to be a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet man and one that had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> whom he viſited ſo often, took an occaſion to tell him how much his family was ingag'd to S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> and that he deſign'd to have him his ſon in law, though he ſeem'd not very fond of the alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. The Captain glad of this confidence reſolv'd to make good uſe of it, he preſently fell to giving him Counſel, and offer'd to ſpeak of the buſineſs to the <hi>Frenchman,</hi> which the Father accepted of with a great deal of pleaſure. The <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> being now become mediator in the affair conſulted <hi>Mariana</hi> what anſwer he ſhould return her
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152700:38"/>Father from S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> and amus'd the good man with delays and put-offs to gain time for a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble occaſion, for <hi>Mariana</hi> to declare to her Parents the neceſſity ſhe was under of being marry'd to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. Lovers once Fortunate flatter themſelves with hopes they ſhall continue ſo ſtill: But a Cruel acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, which is ſo troubleſome to Marri'd Women, ſo terrible to maids, and ſometimes fatal to widows, was like to have broken all the meaſures theſe Lovers had taken. <hi>Mariana</hi> found her ſelf troubl'd with qualms, and with fitts occaſion'd by the familiarities of the <hi>Italian,</hi> ſo that ſhe thought it high time to make her Parents ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it: and believing her mother more tender and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate (in ſuch caſes eſpecially) ſhe confeſs'd ingenuouſly the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhe was in, and was ſo far from complaining of him who had
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152700:38"/>caus'd it that ſhe extold his merit in very paſſionate terms; praying her to keep the buſineſs private, her Lover who had promis'd her marriage, having important rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to conceal it for ſome time. The Mother thinking ſhe ſpoke of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> was ſo far from blaming her daughter that ſhe excuſed the matter, and promis'd to ſpeak it to her Father, that order might be taken to have them privately mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed. The honeſt <hi>Fleming</hi> was ſo glad of the news of a marriage he ſo paſſionately wiſh'd for; that he preſently ſent for a notary to draw the Marriage-ſetlement, wherein he gave his Daughter very great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages in favour of her pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Husband that was to be: The two Lovers had ſign'd, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had the pen in hand for the ſame purpoſe, but miſſing S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins</hi> name in the contract; he told the Notary he had obſerv'd on the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152700:39"/>like occaſions that the parties to be married firſt writ their names, and others afterwards to make good the contract as Parents or Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or to render it authentick as witneſſes: Having ſo ſaid he gave the Notary the Pen, which put <hi>Mariana</hi> into a terrible fright, and all the wit the <hi>Italian</hi> had taught her was little enough to help her out: ſhe told her Father S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was the name of a place, but that the Name he found in the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was that of his Family. This convinc'd the Father that he took the pen again and ſign'd the deed. Being one of the moſt conſiderable Burgeſſes of the town, and willing to pay a reſpect to the Governour, he prayd the Captain who ſtood by, and paſt for S. <hi>Aubins</hi> good friend to accompany the Notary to Count <hi>magalotts,</hi> and deſire his leave for the Marriage: The Governour having been poſſeſt of the thing by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152700:39"/>the Captain, and glad an officer of merit had found an occaſion to make his fortune, readily gave his conſent, and agreed the Ceremony ſhould be perform'd that evening in his Chappel. <hi>Mariana</hi> had the wit to order her buſineſs ſo well, that her Parents went not to the Chappel, but rely'd on an Aunt of hers ſhe had gain'd: This was done with ſuch ſpeed, that S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie'd in the imaginations of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iana's</hi> Parents before ever he heard of it. The Mother gave ſo ſtrict a charge to all her family, to keep the matter private, that every one thought himſelf ſole confident of the intrigue: while the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were a doing, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew to his ordinary retirement. A maid who open'd him the door, deſirous to inſinuate her ſelf into his favour, whom ſhe look'd upon as her new Maſter, wiſh'd him joy: The Father ſeeing him enter, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152700:40"/>thinking that out of respect to him he was loth to appear to him, till he had repair'd his Daughters honour, embrac'd him with great tranſports of Joy. <hi>Mariana's</hi> mother having ſpi'd her imaginary ſon-in-Law, would not give her Husband time to ſpeak, but took him about the neck, calling him her dear Son. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> who underſtood not the meaning of their troubleſome car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſes, thought them mad. As he was going to anſwer their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent diſcourſe, a friend of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily who alone was made privy to the buſineſs prevented him by giving him Joy: never was man more perplex'd than S. <hi>Aubin.</hi> He prai'd them ſeriouſly to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiv'd one for all, ſince for very ſubſtantial reaſons it was not in his power to marry their daughter. The Mother angry at ſo unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a declaration, reply'd that ſince thoſe reaſons had not been ſtrong
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152700:40"/>enough to keep him from diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouring her Daughter, they were too weak to dispence with his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying her; adding, if he did it not, ſhe would puniſh their infamy by ſtrangling them both with her own hands: The quarrell increas'd, and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was in danger of being ill us'd had not the Governour come in with the new-marryed couple. This looks ſo like the laſt ſcene of a Comedy that the Reader will ſcarce believe it. But I pretend not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over mens opinions, I allow e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one Liberty to think what he pleaſes. My Memoires tell me <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana</hi> fell at her parents feet and preſented them her Husband, whom they were oblig'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, the marriage having been celebrated with all the formality uſual, and <hi>Mariana</hi> in a very hopeful condition to make them Grandſires in a ſhort time. At laſt they were all ſatisfi'd, the <hi>Italian</hi> that he had got a good fortune,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152700:41"/>
                  <hi>Mariana,</hi> that ſhe was Married to whom ſhe lov'd; and S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> that he was delivered from her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents perſecutions.</p>
               <p>But the mind of Man is never content, and the <hi>Italian,</hi> (like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ingenious in tormenting themſelves) though he ſaw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter, by his Marriage, of a conſiderable Fortune, and far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his hopes; comparing the plentifulneſs of his preſent Fortune, with thoſe former wants all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry was ſcarce able to preſerve him from, he had a Crotchet in his Pate; there was ſomething more than ordinary in the matter, that a Gentleman of <hi>Bergamo,</hi> no otherwiſe conſiderable than for a Company of Foot which he had gain'd by the ordinary means, ſhould Marry a rich Heireſs, unleſs there were ſome ſecret reaſons for it. In a word, his good Fortune had ſo refin'd his Fancy, that he paſs'd the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152700:41"/>ſame judgment of his Wife moſt Men do, whoſe Wives ſuffer them before-hand to know what they ſhould have been ignorant of till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Wedding, and imagin'd <hi>Mariana</hi> had been as kind to ſome other as to him. Of all he could think of, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> appear'd the moſt likely to be the Man: Having conſider'd it well, he applauded himſelf ſecretly for his penetration, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in his opinion that he had but S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s leavings, and was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding for his ſettlement to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana</hi>'s being with Child; who, not daring to let her Parents know it, reſolv'd to be Marry'd to him, when S. <hi>Aubin</hi> had refus'd her: He doubted not but they had long held Correſpondence, and continu'd it; and loath to be any longer their Cully, reſolv'd to obſerve their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> who had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avoided being alone with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riana,</hi> that ſhe might not have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152700:42"/>to think he lov'd her, was often in her company after ſhe was Marry'd; the reaſon for abſenting himſelf being now over, and her Converſation more witty than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, ſo that having reaſonable good Company at home, he thought he might well ſave himſelf the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſeeking it abroad. S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s Aſſiduities with <hi>Mariana,</hi> gave the Captain new umbrage: He durſt not yet complain of it to <hi>Mariana,</hi> or forbid her his company: his Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie the while repreſented the moſt innocent Actions as criminal. He was the more troubled to ſee moſt of the <hi>French</hi> Gentry in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> going for <hi>Paris,</hi> when S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> who probably had no great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> ſaid not a word of returning for <hi>France,</hi> for which he could not imagine any cauſe, but a Correſpondence with his Wife: He watch'd them ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, that he quickly perceiv'd
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152700:42"/>S. <hi>Aubin</hi> often imploy'd the <hi>Ligeois</hi> into the Country, and at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn quitted all buſineſs to ſpeak with him. The Captain's ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions made him fearful of every Shadow: He was very deſirous to know what buſineſs the <hi>Ligeois</hi> was ſent about, and gave order to an <hi>Italian</hi> Foot-Boy, a very truſty Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, to hide himſelf in S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s Chamber, and hearken diligently what the <hi>Ligeois</hi> ſaid. The Foot-Boy did as he was Commanded, and reported to his Maſter that the <hi>Ligeois</hi> ſaid not a word, but gave S. <hi>Aubin</hi> a Letter which he read very attentively, and ſigh'd often in reading it. The Captain, well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Love-tricks, was ſo poſſeſt with Jealouſie, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently fancy'd the Letters were his Wife's, who perhaps had ſome Confident in the Town who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd them to the <hi>Ligeois.</hi> This ſuſpicion, how ill-grounded ſoever,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152700:43"/>gave our <hi>Italian</hi> no ſmall diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. He reſolv'd to find out the bottom of the buſineſs; and, with the help of the Foot-Boy, found the means one day to draw the <hi>Ligeois</hi> into a Chamber of the Houſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what remote from S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Lodging-room: Having lock'd him up there, he threatned to run him preſently through, if he would not tell him truly whence the Letters came he carry'd S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> ſo often: The <hi>Ligeois</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what Relation S. <hi>Aubin</hi> had to the Marqueſs, but judging by the good uſage of the one, and liberality of the other, that the buſineſs was of Moment, was very loath to anſwer him; underſtanding how dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a matter it is to hold Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with an Enemy, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in a place of War. The trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the <hi>Ligeois</hi> appear'd in height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Italian</hi>'s Curioſity, that he repeated his threats, and put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152700:43"/>in a poſture to execute them. The <hi>Ligeois</hi> affrighted at it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to tell him all if he would but ſave his life: The <hi>Italian</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd it, and the Wretch made him acquainted with the Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between S. <hi>Aubin</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra.</hi> The Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſurpriz'd at the news, made no doubt but they held intelligence againſt the State, and was glad at heart for ſo favourable an occaſion to be reveng'd of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> under a pretence of zeal for the King's ſervice. The ſmalleſt things are of conſequence in matters of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo that notwithſtanding his promiſe to the contrary, he made no ſcruple of ſecuring the <hi>Ligeois,</hi> the Maxims of <hi>Italy</hi> having taught him he was not oblig'd to be a ſlave to his word: He advertis'd the Governour; who, having que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd the <hi>Ligeois,</hi> ſent an Officer, with fifty Souldiers, to arreſt S.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152700:44"/>
                  <hi>Aubin,</hi> who had receiv'd notice the <hi>Ligeois</hi> was a Priſoner; and though he knew not the reaſon, yet he apprehended he might have let fall ſomething in diſcourſe about the Letters he brought him: and that they might not be ſeen, he burnt them; but it went ſo much againſt the grain, and he did it ſo ſlowly, that he was buſie about this cruel Sacrifice, when the Officer ſent to take him entred his Chamber, and after a ſorry Complement or two led him into Priſon. The Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer fail'd not to give the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour an account what he found in S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s Chamber, and what a ſight of Letters there was in the Fire. This laſt Circumſtance made every one think him Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and that he had burnt the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to prevent their being made uſe of as evidence againſt him. This buſineſs made a great noiſe, and, as 'tis uſual on ſuch occaſions for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152700:44"/>one to add ſomething to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, this rais'd the news that paſs'd then currant, of a great Plot diſcover'd at <hi>Valenciennes.</hi> The <hi>Ligeois</hi> was examin'd very ſtrictly, and ſo frightned with the tortures they threatned to put him to, that he confeſs'd all he knew, and a great deal more: His frequent Journeys to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, the Money received from a General of the Enemies, and the burning of the Letters were evidences ſo clear, in the opinion of the Publick, that no doubt was made both the Wretches would ſhortly ſuffer. S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s good Meen, and Curioſity, gain'd him Compaſſion from all that ſaw him: Every one pity'd, but none durſt excuſe him, for fear of being brought in as acceſſary to ſo tickliſh a Crime. He was the while under extreme perplexity in Priſon, every thing ſeem'd to fall out croſs: His ſtay at <hi>Valenciennes</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:152700:45"/>was look'd upon as myſterious, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after he had declar'd he had no deſign to Marry <hi>Mariana.</hi> It was hard to juſtifie himſelf without confeſſing his Sex, which he could ſcarce find in his heart to do. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examin'd, he defended himſelf with ſaying he had written to the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> as his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Friend; but that his Letters had nothing in them that related to the King, or the State. The Judges were not ſatisfied with his anſwer, and perhaps would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd him, had not the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour interpos'd his Authority, at the requeſt of ſome Ladies, to have the judgment ſuſpended till he might receive orders from the Court.</p>
               <p>As they ſeiz'd what was in S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s Chamber, an Officer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Governour had the Curioſity to read ſome Books found there. Among the reſt he read
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152700:45"/>the <hi>Heroine Muſqueteer,</hi> where he ſaw the names of the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſo often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, that he fancy'd S. <hi>Aubin</hi> the Priſoner might be the ſame with S. <hi>Aubin Chriſtina.</hi> He told the Governour, and ſhew'd him the Book. The Governour read it with pleaſure; and having, amongſt S. <hi>Aubin</hi>'s things, found a very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Letter of the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyra</hi>'s, perhaps the only one had eſcap'd the Fire, he was fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was the <hi>Heroine Muſqueteer,</hi> but was willing to be further aſſur'd of it. He ſent for the Priſoner, ſhew'd him the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and told him he doubted not but that which appear'd only a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of kindneſs, was a Cypher to cover ſome matter of State. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſhew'd him ſo many reaſons to the contrary, that the Governour believ'd him incapable of holding intelligence againſt his allegiance;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152700:46"/>but demanded of him a Letter to the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra,</hi> to forbid further Correſpondence. This Propoſal put S. <hi>Aubin</hi> to the groan; and not able to give a good reaſon for refuſing to write ſo, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd ſo diſorder'd, that he thought it might be juſtly taken for a clear conviction of his Crime, yet this trouble juſtifi'd him more than all his Eloquence: For the Governour imputing it to his love, diſcover'd him to be <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and no longer criminal. The buſineſs was huſh'd up, and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſet at liberty. The whole Town was glad of it, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <hi>Mariana's</hi> Parents, who ſtill had kindneſs for him, and had been afraid to loſe him, the <hi>Italian</hi> had taken ſuch care to inform them daily of ſome new Circumſtance of his Crime.</p>
               <p>While S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was in Priſon, the Captain, who made account to have his revenge of S. <hi>Aubin</hi> in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152700:46"/>the puniſhment the State would inflict on him, could not forbear telling his wife ſomething of it, and at the ſame time reproaching her with her falſeneſs. A reproach a Woman truly vertuous is moſt ſenſible of: And the Husband who uſes ſuch language to his Wife, doth but raiſe in her a deſire to be reveng'd of an unjuſt ſuſpition by real diſloyalty, when ſhe ſees him make ſo ſlght account of the reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ſhe values her ſelf upon: <hi>Mariana,</hi> who no otherwiſe knew of any diſloyalty but by her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands diſcourſe, and could reproach her ſelf for nothing but having been too credulous, was ſo touch'd to the quick with her Husbands ingratitude, that ſhe reſolv'd to puniſh him for his Jealouſie; it was long ere her reſentment maſter'd her vertue, being unreſolv'd whom to make choice of to aſſiſt her in her revenge: But when S. <hi>Aubin</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:152700:47"/>was ſet at liberty, ſhe fixt her choice on him; and loooking on him as an Inſtrument very fit for her turn, ſhe us'd him more obligingly than uſual: Every day ſhe reſolv'd to make him acquainted with her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, but when they were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe had not the power to do it, flattering her ſelf perhaps he would gueſs at it. After vain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation he would ſave her the confuſion a complement of that nature would put her in, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him at length with the injuſtice of her Husband, but had not the power to ſay all ſhe intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhame ſtopt her mouth; and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> contented himſelf with blaming the <hi>Italian,</hi> without mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any offer of his ſervice to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her hopes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mariana</hi> not diſcourag'd at this, added, a man of his humour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to have a wife that would be reveng'd of him. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> repli'd
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152700:47"/>coldly, it was an honeſt womans part to think more of her duty to her ſelf than her Husband. This would be ſufficient to keep her from any act of diſloyalty, and for his part he little valu'd a woman who was reſerv'd on no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count but that of her Husband. <hi>Mariana</hi> who expected S. <hi>Aubin</hi> would have offer'd to go halves in the revenge ſhe deſign'd, was extremely ſurpriz'd to hear him preach honeſty to her. And not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to endure longer the vexation it gave her, retir'd into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to weep it out there.</p>
               <p>'Tis natural to deſire what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears difficult to obtain. S. <hi>Aubins</hi> reſiſtance heightned <hi>Marianas</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: to juſtify the diſcretion of her Lover; ſhe fanci'd he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her thus, only to pleaſe her, who he knew was no Lover of very free diſcourſe: I ſhould have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd my ſelf better, ſays ſhe,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152700:48"/>how elſe ſhould a man I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways us'd hardly perceive a ſudden change ſo much to his advantage. With that ſhe reſolv'd to ſpeak more plainly, having obſerv'd her time to make a new tryal, ſhe told him ſhe had reflected on what he had ſaid to her of honeſt womens duty to themſelves, but found thoſe reaſons too weak to reſiſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a predominant paſſion. I cannot indure my Husband, and the deſire I have to be reveng'd of a man who makes ſo ill acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of what I have done for him, makes me forget all I would have regarded on another occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And ſince I am extremely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to make choice of a diſcreet man, I have pitch'd upon you: ſhe ſtopt there, thinking ſhe had ſaid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> who at firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not what revenge ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, thought ſhe would have made away her Husband, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152700:48"/>ſo violent a deſign, blam'd her extremely, telling her, a Wife muſt bear much with her Husband, that the happieſt marriages are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with trouble; and that if all Wives who are not ſatisfi'd with their Husbands ſhould take ſuch violent reſolutions, no man would dare marry; adding, he would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly adventure his life againſt any one had offended her, but that he thought it not the part of a wiſe wan to meddle between Husband and wife. And leaving <hi>Mariana</hi> (in the diſſorder you may imagine) he thought fit to acquaint her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents with the paſſages, and to take meaſures with them to prevent further inconvenience; but he had the diſcretion to tell them no more than that they would do well to prevent diſſorders mightariſe out of ſome ſmall difference between the <hi>Italian</hi> and his wife, for he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd they were both too much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152700:49"/>to quarrel: S. <hi>Aubin</hi> at their requeſt took it upon him to ſpeak to the Captain, and advis'd them the mean time to calm <hi>Mariana;</hi> he found out the <hi>Italian,</hi> and having told him he had ſomething of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to acquaint him with, he made him a long diſcourſe of the extravagant humours of moſt women, and the unhappineſs of Husbands, who have not the art of complying with their weakneſſes, inſinuating it was a wiſe mans part to prevent noiſe, and cover hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely the extravagances of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourſome woman; the <hi>Italian</hi> not knowing what the diſcourſe tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to; took it worſe from S. <hi>Aubin</hi> than he would from any man, fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying he intended to inſult over him, by reproaching him with the eaſineſs of his wife. Being a man of courage he had not the patience to endure the affront, but laid his hand on his Sword, without giving
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152700:49"/>S. <hi>Aubin</hi> time to finiſh the diſcourſe, S. <hi>Aubin</hi> ſtood upon his guard, and defended himſelf, but they were part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without advantage on either ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marianas</hi> Parents tyr'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with preaching to her to live in peace with her Husband, when a Servant brings them news of a duel between S. <hi>Aubin</hi> and the <hi>Italian,</hi> which ſurpriz'd them all, though on different accounts: The Father-in-law believ'd his Son had ill taken the good offices S. <hi>Aubin</hi> would have done him, and ſo oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd the quarrel: <hi>Mariana</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying all to her love, fanci'd S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> had a generoſity refin'd to that extremity that he pretended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unconcern'd for her that he might be in in a condition the better to vindicate her. But the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſhe expected was of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nature, ſuch as ſhe intended to ſhare in the pleaſure of it with him who took it. The Captain
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152700:50"/>arriving, complain'd to <hi>Mariana's</hi> Father of the injury he pretended done him by S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> and told him he would no longer endure the inſolence of that <hi>Frenchman,</hi> who abus'd the reſpect they had for him. The Father heard his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints with attention, and was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at the news of an intrigue between his Daughter and S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> which might be likely enough: The Governour being told of the quarrel, ſent for the Captain, who confidently told him the reaſons he had to draw upon S. <hi>Aubin.</hi> The Governour not able to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Laughing at a jealouſie ſo ill grounded, brought the Captain to himſelf, by telling him S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was a woman.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Aubin</hi> perceiving the ſecret he was ſo careful to conceal, was grown puplick, left <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> and went to <hi>Mons,</hi> being about five Leagues off, giving out he
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152700:50"/>was an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman, related to the houſe of <hi>Crouy:</hi> The Duke of <hi>Arſchot</hi> who was Covernour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd him very kindly: and as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtful as he was of ſtrangers in a Gariſon of that importance, he could not believe a young Gentleman of ſo good a meen capable of any ill deſign. A <hi>Walloon</hi> Collonel, who had ſerv'd in <hi>England,</hi> was very civil to him; and the morrow after his arrival invited him to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was no ſooner come into the Collonels houſe, but he ſaluted his wife, ſhe was a Lady too well qualifi'd to be capable of ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and having been with her Husband at <hi>Cambray</hi> when it was taken, ſhe preſently knew S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> to be the Mareſchal <hi>Luxembourgs Aid de Camp,</hi> who had complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Ladies there from his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; ſhe was extremely glad to ſee him, and to have that occaſion to expreſs her acknowledgment of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152700:51"/>his civilities: She fancy'd her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, to pleaſe her with the ſurprize, had brought him in as an <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> and ſhe, to be even with her Husband, ask'd S. <hi>Aubin</hi> (as if ſhe had not known him) what News from <hi>England.</hi> S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving himſelf diſcover'd, anſwer'd very naturally, and like a Man of that Country, affecting to ſpeak broken <hi>French,</hi> and giving ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act an account of Affairs, that the Collonel's Wife thought her ſelf miſtaken, in taking him to be S. <hi>Aubin:</hi> She excus'd her ſelf for it, and her Husband made her miſtake the Subject of his Raillery all Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-time. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouſly eſcap'd diſcovery here, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd not to appear before the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs of <hi>Arſchot,</hi> knowing ſhe had great Relations at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and would not fail to let her Friends know of it. He gave the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> notice of his being at <hi>Mans</hi> by this Letter.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:152700:51"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The difficulties I found in receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing news of you, and giving you an account of my ſelf, made me reſolve to come hither. Your Campaign is at an end, and I am in a Town you have no ſuſpicion of: Conſult your love, and tell me what I ſhall do to keep within the Rules of Decency. I will wait your anſwer before I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the Ducheſs of</hi> Arſchots, <hi>that I may not expoſe my ſelf to the noiſe may be thereby occaſion'd; And you ſhall find, under the Name of S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Your</hi> Chriſtina.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>S. <hi>Aubin</hi> having ſent this Letter to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> by a truſty Meſſenger, reſolv'd to wait an anſwer in his Chamber, but was deceiv'd: For the Collonel's Wife having viſited the Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot,</hi> for want of other diſcourſe, told her of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman, who had ſupp'd the Night before at her Houſe,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152700:52"/>and how ſhe miſtook him for a <hi>French</hi> Gentleman ſhe had ſeen at <hi>Cambray:</hi> Having added a great deal about his Wit and good Meen, ſhe rais'd in the Ducheſs a deſire to ſee him. The Collonel undertook to bring him to her, found him in his Chamber, and having magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd the good ſervice his Wife had done, in giving the Ducheſs a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of his good qualities, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to bring him to the Ducheſs. S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> vext at his officiouſneſs, excus'd himſelf with ſaying his Head ak'd. The Collonel, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected not a refuſal, and had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd to bring him, preſs'd him to go along, aſſuring him he ſhould not ſtay a Moment. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was perplext, being loth to ſee the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs before he had an anſwer to his Letter, and not well able to get rid of the Collonel's importunity, he pray'd him to allow him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time of reſt, and he would go
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152700:52"/>with him in the Evening. The Collonel went away well ſatisfi'd with the promiſe, and S. <hi>Aubin</hi> continued unreſolv'd what to do. Having thought well of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and knowing the Ducheſs a generous Perſon, he choſe rather to ſee her privately, and be known to her; than expoſe himſelf pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly to the ſurprize his diſguiſe might occaſion. He left his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber before the Collonel return'd, and being got to the Ducheſſes, ſent her word there was a Stranger had buſineſs of conſequence with her, and deſir'd private Audience: The Ducheſs went preſently into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Room, where S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was ſoon after admitted. As ſoon as S. <hi>Aubin</hi> appear'd, the Ducheſs at firſt ſight knew who it was; and without allowing her time to ſpeak, kindly embrac'd her, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing much joy to ſee her. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> gave her a brief account of Affairs,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152700:53"/>and the deſign brought him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and thinking it better to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> in Maids Habit, pray'd the Ducheſs admittance once more into her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; which the Ducheſs readily granted. All things agreed on, the Gentleman made as if he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew; and preſently after return'd by another Door the Ducheſs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to be open'd on purpoſe. S. <hi>Aubin</hi> had provided a Suit of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Cloaths at <hi>Paris,</hi> and having quickly ſhifted the Habit and Name of S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> into that of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> the Ducheſs produc'd her as a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman of <hi>Lille,</hi> who was come to ſpend ſome time with her. It is the Prerogative of Great ones to be believ'd without examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Particulars by Inferiours; and <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was taken by all, for what the Ducheſs declar'd her to be. The Duke of <hi>Arſchot</hi> was the firſt deceiv'd: The Collonel in the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152700:53"/>mean time was return'd to S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi>'s Lodging, where he was told the Gentleman was gone. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting then on what had paſs'd at Table, he made no doubt but the pretended <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> was the <hi>French-man</hi> his Wife had ſeen at <hi>Cambray.</hi> He was ſorry he had been ſo credulous, and reſolv'd not to appear at the Governour's, for fear of being ask'd news of the Stranger. The Ducheſs, willing to divert her ſelf with the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſent for the Collonel and told him, that being his Friend, ſhe took that occaſion to let him know the Duke was much ſurpriz'd to hear he held Correſpondence with the Enemy, and had entertain'd at his Houſe, at Supper the laſt Night, a <hi>French</hi> Spy, though his Wife knew him to be an <hi>Aid de Camp</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi>'s. The good Collonel, aſtoniſh'd at the diſcourſe, pray'd the Ducheſs to continue his
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152700:54"/>Protectoreſs; aſſuring her, by all that's ſacred, he was innocent, and had taken that young Gentleman to be an <hi>Engliſh man.</hi> The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, pretending her ſelf ſatisfi'd, promis'd to clear him.</p>
               <p>The Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot,</hi> fearing to draw trouble on her ſelf, writ to one of her Friends at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring advice how to govern her ſelf, as to <hi>Chriſtina;</hi> and whether the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would not take it ill ſhe entertain'd a <hi>French-woman.</hi> The Ducheſs <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> ſaw the Letter, and ſhe told her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of it. The Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyra</hi> was in the mean time gone to <hi>Mons,</hi> in ſearch of S. <hi>Aubin;</hi> but could have no account what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him. The Collonel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of the Marqueſs's arrival, waited on him to tender his ſervice; but finding him troubled S. <hi>Aubin</hi> was gone, he thought they had diſcover'd ſome Plot, and made
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152700:54"/>haſte away for fear of being appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended as having had a hand in it. The Marqueſs could not, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, be long at <hi>Mons</hi> without viſiting the Duke and Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot:</hi> He went to their Houſe, and was receiv'd with all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect due to his Birth and Merit. The Ducheſs, who gueſs'd the cauſe of his coming, perceiving, by the diſtraction appearing in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, the trouble he was in, told him they had that day ſurpriz'd a <hi>French</hi> Spy, drawing a Map of the Town; and that ſhe had much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do to prevail with her Husband not to cauſe him to be hang'd up immediately. The Marqueſs full of fear for S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> ask'd her, with much trouble, what was become of the Criminal. You may queſtion him if you pleaſe, ſays the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, for he is yet in my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and I am ſure you will be for giving him his Life: Having paſs'd
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152700:55"/>into another Apartment, There is the Criminal, ſays the Ducheſs, ſhewing him <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> The Reader may well think they embrac'd one another e're ſhe could make an end of her Complement. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> charming as ſhe was, appear'd much more ſo to the Marqueſs. They were both ſo well ſatisfi'd at the ſight of each other, after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny croſs Accidents, that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſome time looking one upon another, not able to ſpeak a word to expreſs their joy. They fail'd not afterwards to ſay all the kind things two Lovers are capable of on ſuch an occaſion. The Marqueſs thank'd the Ducheſs for the pleaſant Cheat put upon him, and confeſs'd he was come with a deſign to Marry his dear Miſtreſs, and pray'd her the Ceremony of it might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd at her Houſe. The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, not expecting ſo ſudden a Reſolution, could not handſomly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152700:55"/>refuſe him; but deſir'd time to think on't, and to receive an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer from <hi>Bruſſels;</hi> adding, he would do well to ſend a Courrier to the Biſhop for a Licenſe. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> ſaying ſhe thought that very neceſſary, and deſir'd it might be ſo; the Marqueſs ſent away a Gentleman expreſs to the Biſhop, and charg'd him to diſpatch that Affair with all expedition. The two Lovers, with a pleaſing impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, expected the return of the Courrier, and rejoic'd the while to ſee their Conſtancy ſo near be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Crown'd with mutual Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Marqueſs was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s thoughts were altogether Heroick, that ſhe lov'd none beſide him, and was above the weakneſſes commonly incident to thoſe of her Sex. How odd ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it might appear, that a Man of his Quality ſhould Marry a Maid that had run through ſo many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152700:56"/>Adventures, his love, and the knowledge he had of the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of his Miſtreſs, prevail'd with him above all other conſiderations. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who had not on any other occaſion been ſenſible of Love, but yielded her ſelf to the ſole merit and perſeverance of the Marqueſs, was extreme glad to ſee her trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſo near an end, and her ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the point of being united to the only Man of the World, who had the ſecret to pleaſe her, and ſhe thought worthy of her affections: But this Joy was ſhort-liv'd, and the ſatisfaction they had to be together ſome hours, ſeem'd granted them only to heighten the grief that was quickly to ſucceed upon their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from each other, with ſmall hopes of ever ſeeing one another again.</p>
               <p>The Ducheſs of <hi>Benavidez,</hi> who, after the taking of <hi>Cambray,</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd into <hi>Spain,</hi> and could not
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:152700:56"/>pardon the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> his inſenſibility, had inform'd his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Paſſion he had for <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> and had given her ſo ill-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd a Deſcription of that poor Maids Diſguiſes and Adventures, that the Mother was perſwaded her Son was bewitch'd: And at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing his Paſſion to ſomething ſupernatural, ſhe pray'd <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> (who had a reſpect for her, having long known her at <hi>Arragon,</hi>) to obtain an Order from the King, to the Governour of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> to obſtruct the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Marqueſs with <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> and (if need were) to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King's Authority to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it. The Order was ſent into <hi>Flanders,</hi> as ſtrict as the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs could wiſh it, and the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa,</hi> very zealous for the ſervice of his Prince, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to demonſtrate an exact Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Orders of the Court,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152700:57"/>and repair, by performing what was in his power, the misfortune he had to loſe many places it was not in his power to defend better than he had done; being adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, by the Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot</hi>'s Letter, of <hi>Chriſtina's</hi> arrival at <hi>Mons,</hi> preſently ſent thither the Captain of his Guards, with the King's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der addreſs'd to the Duke of <hi>Arſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chot,</hi> declaring he muſt be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the King to have <hi>Chriſtina</hi> forth-coming. And being told the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> was gone from <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> he preſently thought him gone for <hi>Mons;</hi> which oblig'd him to diſpatch a Courrier thither, to tell the Marqueſs he muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently attend him. The Courrier arriv'd as ſoon as the King's Order; and the Marqueſs (from whom the Duke conceal'd the Order he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd) believ'd the <hi>French</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to attacque <hi>Bruſſels;</hi> and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in all haſte, having taken leave
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152700:57"/>of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and recommended her earneſtly to the Ducheſs. When the Marqueſs came to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> he was extremely ſurpriz'd when the Governour ſhew'd him the Order from <hi>Spain,</hi> and pray'd him not to ſtir out of Town; for if he did, he muſt interpoſe his Authority to hinder him. The Marqueſs was upon the point of returning for <hi>Mons</hi> in ſpight of the Governour's orders, when a Letter was brought him from the Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot,</hi> acquainting him ſhe was much troubled a Higher Power had put it out of hers to expreſs her reſpects for him in the Perſon of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, who was now in a Covent, where ſhe ſhould be us'd very civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but was not to be ſpoke with by any but the Abbeſs of the place, the Order from <hi>Spain</hi> being poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in that Particular. This was a deadly blow to a Man in Love, as the Marqueſs; but it muſt be born
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:152700:58"/>with, and he muſt be content to write into <hi>Spain</hi> to endeavour to obtain a Revocation of the Order. Several Perſons of the higheſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity writ in favour of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her the Character of an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Perſon; and that her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and excellent Qualities, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be us'd with particular reſpect. The good Offices intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Marqueſs by Letters ſo much to the advantage of his Miſtreſs, had an effect quite contrary to his Friends expectation. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> having been told of her, and ſcarce believing what was reported of her, expreſs'd a great deſire to ſee ſo rare a Perſon: And having ask'd if it were not poſſible to have her brought into <hi>Spain, Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> promis'd ſhe ſhould. It being <hi>Don John</hi>'s Cuſtom to make the King acquainted with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Affairs of <hi>Europe,</hi> by way of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement; as in the beginning
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152700:58"/>of his Miniſtry he made him deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to learn to write, by ſhewing him a Letter from the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> all of the Hand-writing of that young Prince; and aſſuring his Majeſty he might, if he pleas'd, do as much in three Months. The King thought well of it, and learnt to write. Order was ſent to the Governour of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> to Embarque <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd into <hi>Spain:</hi> the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa,</hi> willing to ſave the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> the trouble the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving his Miſtreſs to ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance might occaſion him, kept this Order very private. When <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was told ſhe muſt go a Ship-board, ſhe was at Death's-door; eſpecially when ſhe heard ſhe was to go into <hi>Spain</hi> and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs to ſtay in <hi>Elanders,</hi> with ſo little hopes of ever ſeeing her more. Theſe Reflections made her forgot ſhe had ever been S. <hi>Aubin,</hi> and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152700:59"/>yield her ſelf wholly to the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Chriſtina;</hi> her love draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tears from her in abundance, which the fear of Death was never able to force from her. She took Shipping at <hi>Oſtend,</hi> in a Veſſel fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and arm'd, on purpoſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey her for <hi>Spain.</hi> She was recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended with ſo much care to the Officers of the Ship, that they thought her a Princeſs of ſome So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Family, which the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> had ſtolen away for reaſons of State. The Gentry of that Nation are great adorers of Women, and thoſe in the Ship us'd her with that reſpect that help'd her to bear her misfortunes more patiently, a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, what condition ſoever ſhe is in, being ſtill ſenſible of the defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence expreſt for her. An Officer in the Ship (whether Lieutenant, or Enſign, I know not) poſſeſt with an opinion of <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Highneſs, and having perhaps read in <hi>Don
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:152700:59"/>Quixot,</hi> that the firſt duty of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier is to ſuccour Ladies in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, obſerving <hi>Chriſtina</hi> one day all bloated with crying, watch'd an opportunity to ſpeak to her in private, and told her if ſhe was ſo averſe againſt going to <hi>Spain,</hi> as her tears and her ſighs gave him cauſe to believe, ſhe might ſignifie her pleaſure to him, who would bring her where ſhe deſir'd, or ſet fire of the Ship. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the extravagance of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in what concerns Ladies, doubted not but he ſpake in good earneſt; but looking on his Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal as impracticable, ſhe thank'd him, pretending ſhe would not conſent to it, for fear of expoſing a Gentleman of ſo much bravery to ſo certain danger. Who ever knows the humour of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will eaſily believe ſuch an anſwer, from a fair Lady, was more than ſufficient to oblige this Officer to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152700:60"/>undertake impoſſibilities for her ſake: He conjur'd her to employ him in her ſervice, aſſuring her he would endeavour to anſwer the good opinion ſhe had of his worth. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> unwilling to act any thing raſhly, advis'd him to conſider a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the matter; and becauſe they could not, without ſuſpicion, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe long together, ſhe pray'd him to put in writing the means he thought proper to bring about his deſign by: The Officer promis'd it, and withdrew to perform it. As he was drawing up his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial two Veſſels of <hi>Tripoly</hi> attack'd the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ship: I will not trouble the Reader with a tedious Relation of the Sea-fight, but acquaint him only that <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> chuſing rather to go into <hi>Spain,</hi> where ſhe might hope to ſee the Marqueſs <hi>D'Oſſeyra</hi> once more, than to fall into the <hi>Turks</hi> hands, did extraordinary Actions in the Fight; and having
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152700:60"/>obſerv'd a Souldier who ſcarce knew how to handle his Arms, took them out of his hands, and made ſo good uſe of them, that ſhe contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted very much to the ſhameful Retreat the <hi>Turks</hi> were forc'd to make.</p>
               <p>When all was quiet again in the Ship, the Captain and Officers, who all their life had been under the vulgar errour, that a Woman is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of Actions of Valour, were aſtoniſht at <hi>Chriſtina's</hi> dexterity and courage. They Complemented her for it, but having not in their Language Terms ſuficiently expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of their admiration, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd it by looking on her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeaking a word. The <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> are great Bouncers, much given to Hyperboles, one call'd her the Queen of <hi>Amazones,</hi> another ſaid ſhe was an Angel deſcended from Heaven for their aid. They were ſo well ſatisfi'd with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:152700:61"/>ſhe had done (for ſo they call'd them) that had ſhe taken her advantage of the favourable diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition they were then in, ſhe might have eaſily perſwaded them to land her in <hi>France:</hi> But ſhe had a very ſtaid wit, not apt to be led with fancies, ſo that ſhe never thought of it. In the mean time the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer who had offer'd her his ſervice, being confirm'd in the fancy he had of her high Birth, by the Actions he had lately ſeen, took a new reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to ſet her at liberty; and blindly, following his fancy, drew up an extravagant Project, ſuitable to the Capacity of a Man bred ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meanly. It was divided into Articles too ridiculous to be inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The ſubſtance was,</p>
               <p>That he would ſteal <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> by killing the Centinel at her Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin Door; and becauſe this could not be done without noiſe, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he had provided againſt it
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:152700:61"/>by a hole he had made in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazin of Powder, at which he would diſcharge a ſmall Gun, ſet fire of the Powder-Room, and blow up the Veſſel, as ſoon as they were got away, to a convenient diſtance, in the Long-boat. The only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he deſir'd for this brave Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was to be ſent to <hi>London</hi> with the Character of Ambaſſadour from the Princeſs, to deſire his Majeſty of <hi>England</hi>'s Protection. He was ſo pleas'd with the fancy of his Project, that one day he told <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> ſhe would without fail be at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in few days, all things being near ready, and preſented her the Paper; Read it, ſays he, and you will find I have taken my Meaſures very right. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready no great opinion of his wit, receiv'd his Memorial, imagining he might write with more judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than he ſpoke. The extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> would at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:152700:62"/>time have made her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſport: But now ſhe pitty'd his folly; telling him, coldly, her mind was alter'd, and that ſhe was very deſirous to ſee the Court of <hi>Spain.</hi> Any Man, but a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> would have been offended at the ſlight; but what ever happens a <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> finds Fewel in it to feed the Fire of his Vanity: He reply'd ſhe could not do better than go ſee the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court, which, in his opinion, was the moſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick of the Univerſe.</p>
               <p>The Ship this while drew near the Coaſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> not forgetting ſhe was ſtill further and further from the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra,</hi> afflicted her ſelf every day ſo much the more. As ſoon as they landed, the Maſter of the Veſſel took Poſt to carry the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi>'s diſpatches to Court. When he arriv'd there, they ask'd him a hundred ſeveral
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152700:62"/>Queſtions about <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> He ſpoke much in commendation of her beauty, but when he came to the Particulars of the Engagement with the Veſſels of <hi>Tripoli,</hi> he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll'd to the Skies, the valour and courage of our <hi>Heroine.</hi> This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd ſo ſtrange, in a Country where Women ſpend their time in an exceſſive ſoftneſs, and are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally fearful, that all who heard the News, ſpoke of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> with great admiration. He who firſt gave the King an account of her, and occaſion'd his deſire to ſee her, fail'd not to acquaint him with what the Captain ſaid of her: The King was willing to hear the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf, and ſent for him. The King's preſence, and the deſire to pleaſe him, inſpir'd Eloquence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Captain, who gave his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty an account of the Fight, and particularly of what <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had done; which he diſplay'd with
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152700:63"/>ſuch advantage, it heighten'd the King's deſire to ſee her. A Coach of the King's was immediately ſent away, to bring her with more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, and expedition to Court; where, by the diligence of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon employ'd to attend her, <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> arriv'd in very few days.</p>
               <trailer>The end of the Third Part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:152700:63"/>
               <head>THE Heroine Muſqueteer: OR, THE FEMALE WARRIER.</head>
               <head type="sub">The fourth and laſt Part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHRISTINA</hi> being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at <hi>Madrid,</hi> was much troubled to find e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one there ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſirous to ſee her: The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Benavidez</hi> had given ſo ſtrange an account of her, and the Captain of the Veſſel, in which ſhe was tranſported into <hi>Spain,</hi> was ſo careful in publiſhing her
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152700:64"/>Action againſt the Corſaires, (to which the People added ſo many fabulous Circumſtances) that her valour was generally attributed to a ſupernatural principle. Some confidently affirm'd ſhe was a Witch; but this ridiculous report vaniſh'd as ſoon as ſhe appear'd at Court, where ſhe anſwer'd exactly all the Queſtions <hi>Don John of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> ask'd her in the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. She had the good Fortune to ſee whatever ſhe ſpoke was pleaſing and well taken; to which her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, good Meen, and ſpeaking <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſo well, did very much contribute: The Court was well ſatisfy'd with her diſcourſe, and the Prince <hi>Don John of Auſtria</hi> aſſur'd her ſhe ſhould be well us'd, and treated with reſpect: When ſhe was retir'd, the King, and the Prince his Brother, ſpoke much to her advantage: The Courtiers, as well out of a natural inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152700:64"/>the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have to ſpeak always in favour of Ladies, as of cuſtom to approve whatever the King likes, highly applauded his Majeſties ſentiments. They made particular Obſervations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks on all that appeared charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and diſcover'd ſuch excellency of wit in expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons dropt caſually from her, that the King was perſwaded they had done her wrong who had cenſur'd her conduct; and of all thoſe Gentlemen who waited on his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, there was not one but could have wiſh'd himſelf the place of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> in her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: <hi>Don John</hi> gave order ſhe ſhould have Lodging and Dyet at the Kings charge: Theſe diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing favours, and the oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing character given her by thoſe who knew her, made ſeveral La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, of the higheſt Quality, very deſirous to ſee her. 'Tis not to be
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:152700:65"/>expected they ſhould have, for one of their Sex, the complaiſance of Gentlemen, who, taken at firſt ſight with the ſplendour of a beautiful Lady, obſerve not her defects, or at leaſt paſs over and excuſe them: Women, on the contrary, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look, or (at beſt) take very ſlight notice of any thing that appears pleaſing and agreeable in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and apply themſelves with diligence to magnifie and blazon all her imperfections, and whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they believe diſpleaſing or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome. As ſoon as the Ladies had ſeen <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> they blam'd their weak judgments who had cry'd up her beauty, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to make them ſenſible of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral defects in it, though all the World is not yet of theſe Ladies Opinion in the caſe: The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs <hi>de Benavidez</hi> perceiving the preſence of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the ill impreſſions ſhe had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152700:65"/>of her, endeavour'd to prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Courtiers to her diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: But being fruſtrated on that ſide, and looking on the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as better diſpoſed to ſerve her deſign, who are uſually pleas'd to hear any thing to the prejudice of one of their Sex, who has gain'd the reputation of eminent; ſhe ſpoke of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> with that ſcorn and contempt, that ſeveral of the Ladies were unwilling to appear in the ſame Room with her. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diligence of the Counteſs, and the diſcourſe of the Ladies of her Cabal, the young Gentlemen of the Court lik'd <hi>Chriſtina</hi> very well: But the Count <hi>Talara,</hi> firſt Gentleman of his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Majeſties Bed-Chamber, no longer able to ſtifle the Flame kindled in his affections, frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her company, and omitted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to make her ſenſible he was in love with her. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152700:66"/>it, did all that could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from a vertuous Lady to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſe him, and us'd all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes and Arguments, a Woman, who would diſcourage a Lover and had no deſire to be lov'd, could invent on that occaſion: The Count <hi>de Talara,</hi> not diſcouraged by her ſeverities, continued to love and wait upon her wherever ſhe was to be ſeen, being not of the opinion of that experienced Lover, who ſaid it was in a Womans power to deterr any from loving her, by a cold entertainment, and at two or three ſeveral times telling them dryly ſhe was not pleas'd with the addreſs. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having follow'd this maxim, and ſeveral others for curing the Count, thought it in vain to diſcourage him any more, but reſolv'd (without giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf the trouble of unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him further) ſo to order her actions, and ſhape the conduct
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152700:66"/>of her life, as not to give him cauſe of the leaſt hope of ſucceſs: The Count attributing <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s ſlights to ſome particular a verſion he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended ſhe might have againſt him, fancy'd ſhe was otherwiſe inclin'd, and being a Perſon infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to none, in handſomneſs, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or wit, was troubled extremely with this imagination: To ſatisfie himſelf in this particular, he made ſome Perſons, who now and then viſited <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> acquainted with his paſſion, and pray'd them not to ſee her any more. The Gentlemen of <hi>Spain</hi> have that deference and reſpect one for another, that a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of this kind is not extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary there: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> very careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avoided all occaſions of being alone with the Count, and went frequently to Court to entertain his Majeſty with an account of paſſages in <hi>Flanders.</hi> And having one day expreſt a great deſire to ſee
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:152700:67"/>the <hi>Eſcurial,</hi> to know whether that famous Houſe anſwer'd the reputation it had in <hi>Europe;</hi> the King was glad there was any thing in <hi>Spain</hi> could move the curioſity of a Perſon who had ſeen ſo many varieties, and pray'd two Ladies of the Court to bear her company thither, to ſhew her the magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of that Pallace, and the rare deviſes in ſeveral Apartments there, which <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond put ſo great a value upon: Order was given the Ladies ſhould be ſumptuouſly treated there: Count <hi>Talara,</hi> having heard of it, would fain have been one of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but was indiſpenſably oblig'd by the duty of his place to attend the Kings perſon, and as things then ſtood in the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> there was no abſenting himſelf without manifeſt hazard of his Fortune. As he was thinking of a Perſon he might confide in, to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152700:67"/>ſpeak in his favour to <hi>Chriſtina</hi> on this occaſion, news was brought him that the high Steward of the Kings Houſhold, who was his Kinſman and Friend, was newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd from the Army in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> where he had a command; the Count gave him a viſit, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confeſt he was deſperately in love with an excellent ſtrange La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who was to be on the morrow at the <hi>Eſcurial,</hi> with ſeveral other Ladies; he conjur'd him to make uſe of the Priviledge of his place, in going to the entertainment, where it would be in his power to do him good offices with his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, under pretence of taking care of the Ladies. A Gentleman never refuſes an imployment of this nature, and this Friend of the Counts, readily accepting the charge he gave him, promis'd to acquit himſelf well of it. He fail'd not to go the next day to the <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial;</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:152700:68"/>where, having given the neceſſary orders, he went into a Gallery the Ladies were walking in; who, having notice of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, advanc'd to receive him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving he had taken this Journey meerly out of reſpect to them: He had ſcarce begun to paſs a Complement of civility upon them, but having caſt his Eyes on <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> he ſtood ſtill as a Statute: The Ladies were aſtoniſht, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who fixing her Eye earneſtly on him, knew him to be <hi>Don Philip de Palafox,</hi> of whom I ſpoke in my firſt Volume, as the Perſon who paſs'd the <hi>Pyrences</hi> to ſteal her away. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> cry'd out, frightned to ſee her ſelf ſo near a Perſon who had been deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in love with her, and one whom ſhe thought ſhe had highly offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Don Philip</hi> had not heard of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſince he went into the Army in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> whence he
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152700:68"/>return'd but once to Court, to take his Oath of High-Steward of the Houſhold, the place being void by the death of the Marqueſs <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizza</hi> his Father; ſo that 'twas no wonder he was ſurpriz'd at ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected a ſight of a Perſon who had been ſo dear to him, and by her inſenſibility had made him reſolve to go into the Army: Thoſe who have had any experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in Love, will eaſily agree, the ſight, after long abſence, of a perſon we have tenderly lov'd, and never prevail'd with, cannot but cauſe extraordinary emotions in the heart of a Lover. All Men are apt to flatter themſelves in their paſſions, and <hi>Don Palafox,</hi> not able to imagine what ſtrange For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhould bring <hi>Chriſtina</hi> (a <hi>French-woman</hi>) into <hi>Spain,</hi> when the Two Crowns were ſo deeply engag'd in War, preſently fancy'd ſhe had repented her ill uſage of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152700:69"/>him, and probably was return'd into <hi>Spain</hi> in ſearch of him. And continuing to interpret all things to his advantage, he thought the ſlights Count <hi>Talara</hi> complain'd of, and the loud cry her late aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, at firſt ſight of him, had forc'd from her, effects of her paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for him. Being full of theſe fancies, he ſaid a thouſand extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagances; and <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was ſo ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd, ſhe anſwer'd not a word: The Ladies who ſtood by, taking notice of the aſtoniſhment on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, help'd to bring them to themſelves again; and finding <hi>Chriſtina</hi> much diſordered by the preſence of <hi>Don Philip,</hi> they pray'd him to withdraw, which he could not deny them; yet hoped the diſorder he ſaw <hi>Chriſtina</hi> in boded him much good. He was no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er gone, but <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> obſerving that the Ladies were in pain to know the cauſe of her trouble,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152700:69"/>yet ſo diſcreet as to forbear asking her, acquainted them with what had paſt in her Country, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe had any relation to her concern with <hi>Don Philip:</hi> This leſſen'd their wonder at her aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and was eaſily believ'd by them, who were well acquainted with the headſtrong humour of that Gentleman.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Philip</hi> the while conſider'd the accident he had newly met with, and being naturally vain, flatter'd himſelf with an opinion <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was in love with him. It was a pretty while ere he came to a reſolution whether to return to the Ladies, or retire to ſave <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> the confuſion he fear'd his preſence would put her in before the Company: After much debate it was carry'd for the retirement, in confidence his Miſtreſs would thank him for his diſcretion, and eſteem him the better for't. Count
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152700:70"/>
                  <hi>Talara</hi> impatient to hear the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his Friends Journey, had given order he ſhould have notice as ſoon as <hi>Palafox</hi> arriv'd: And go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Houſe ſoon after his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, he ask'd him, with much concern, what news of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs: You have a Rival, anſwer'd <hi>Don Philip,</hi> who hath long been in love with the fair <hi>French woman,</hi> and he is a Gentleman I have a great intereſt in, and my very good Friend. Know you not, reply'd the Count, thinking he meant the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> that the King hath explained himſelf in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and declar'd, he will not conſent to their Marriage: You ſurprize me, ſays <hi>Don Philip,</hi> (not comprehending the Counts mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) I did not think the Court ſo well inform'd of the affair. A Kinſman of <hi>Don Philips</hi> coming in, interrupted their diſcourſe, and prevented farther explication: The
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152700:70"/>Count took his leave, and <hi>Don Pallafox</hi> remained very unquiet at the news he had newly told: Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King on the morrow, he found <hi>Chriſtina</hi> there, giving his Majeſty an account of every thing worthy obſervation at the <hi>Eſcurial:</hi> They ask'd if ſhe thought it a better Houſe than <hi>Verſailles;</hi> there is no proportion between them, ſays <hi>Chriſtina, Verſailles</hi> being more conſiderable for the Waters, and delicate Gardens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, than the magnificence of the Buildings, which are neat and convenient, but not ſtately; but the <hi>Eſcurial</hi> is a Pallace of very large extent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Philip</hi> pretending he knew not this ſtrange Lady, ask'd thoſe who ſtood by who ſhe was, while ſhe ſpoke to the King: They told him what they had heard of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi>'s paſſion, the Fights ſhe had been in, in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:152700:71"/>and, in a word, all thoſe Stories the Publick had added to the truth of her Adventures. The King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone to Counſel, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd, and <hi>Don Philip</hi> gave her his Hand to bring her to her Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which ſhe would not refuſe him, for fear of notice being taken of it in ſo publick a place: As ſoon as he came where he might ſpeak to her in private, he aſſur'd her he had always lov'd her, and that if he had been guilty of diſreſpect in endeavouring to ſteal her, ſhe ought to pardon it, as an effect of the exceſs of his paſſion, his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions having been always very good. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> willing to diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe him, told him his explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were to no purpoſe, ſince ſhe had diſpos'd of her Heart to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and waited only a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opportunity to complain to the King of the injuſtice of her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to intreat his Majeſties
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:152700:71"/>protection, if ſhe ſhould marry the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra;</hi> otherwiſe, that ſhe might have liberty to ſpend her life in a Covent. With that ſhe burſt out into Tears, at the thought of the Marqueſs; which <hi>Don Philip</hi> ſeeing, (that he might not afflict her more by diſcourſe he perceived troubleſome to her) went away, but was ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for her, that he made it his buſineſs to be better inſtructed in the particulars of her affairs.</p>
               <p>Having remembred himſelf that the Counteſs <hi>de Benavidez</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided long in <hi>Flanders,</hi> he gave her a viſit, and falling inſenſibly into diſcourſe of <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> The Counteſs gave him a deſcription of her, much like that ſhe had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly given the Marchioneſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> and many others; inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating that all her diſguiſes were the effects of a criminal paſſion; which <hi>Don Philip</hi> was ſo far perſwaded of, that he repented he had ever lov'd
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:152700:72"/>her: Moſt Men are diſpoſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what they hear reported of the ill conduct of Women, and the groſs Error of moſt ſtrangers, eſpecially <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in the hard cenſures they paſs of the liberty Women enjoy in <hi>France,</hi> did not a little contribute to confirm <hi>Don Philip</hi> in the ſentiments the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs had inſpir'd him with. He thank'd her for her information, and having that Evening met with Count <hi>Talara,</hi> as the King was going to Bed, he told him he would cure him of the paſſion he had for <hi>Christina,</hi> aſſuring him he knew by a very good hand, ſhe was unworthy the affection of a Perſon of Honour: The King ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that Inſtant call'd the Count upon buſineſs belonging to his Place, he had not the time to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <hi>Don Philip;</hi> and preſently after, every body withdrew: The Count, by his priviledge of firſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:152700:72"/>Gentleman of the Bed-Chamber, was to lye there that Night: The paſſion he had for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> made him muſe all Night of <hi>Don Philips</hi> Diſcourſe; at laſt, reproaching himſelf for having endur'd Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſo much to the diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a Perſon he lov'd, he thought himſelf oblig'd, as a Gentleman, to demand ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and got up with a reſolution to fight <hi>Don Philip,</hi> though Duels are forbidden in <hi>Spain:</hi> But the Prince diſpenſing very much with the ſeverity of the Edicts, they are not obſerved there as exactly as in <hi>France,</hi> ſo that Gentlemen fight Duels there on very ſlight occaſions. Count <hi>Talara</hi> having written a Billet to <hi>Don Philip,</hi> he deliver'd it to one of his Servants, a <hi>Navarrois</hi> in whom he plac'd great confidence, commanding him to carry it to <hi>Don Philip:</hi> Challenges being out of faſhion in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:152700:73"/>
                  <hi>France,</hi> I have inſerted the form of this, tranſlated word for word, being as follows.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whoever dares ſpeak to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of</hi> Chriſtina, <hi>lyes: She is of unqueſtionable Vertue; and he cannot be a Man of Honour, who judges otherwiſe of her: If you are of a contrary Opinion, let me find you at one a Clock after Midnight, at the</hi> Toledo-Gate, <hi>where you ſhall receive the Puniſhment due for the wrong judgment you have paſt of her.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The Count recommended this Billet ſo often, and with ſo ſtrict a charge to the Boy, that it gave him the curioſity to know what it contain'd. He was much ſurpriz'd at the reading it, and having been born near <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and heard ſo many extraordinary things of her, he had a kind of inclination for her, and thought he might do her
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:152700:73"/>ſome ſervice in letting her ſee a Billet ſhe was ſo much concern'd in; and ſlipt privately into her Lodging to ſhew it her: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having given him ſome Fruits of her acknowledgment, charg'd him to carry it ſafe to <hi>Don Philip,</hi> and acquaint her with his anſwer, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, (the better to engage him to it) it was of very great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Philip,</hi> having received the Billet, was extremely offended with the outrageous Language the Count had made uſe of, and told the Boy it required no anſwer, but he would give his Maſter an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer at the place appointed. The <hi>Navarrois</hi> gave <hi>Chriſtina</hi> an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and then his Maſter: While the Count was fitting himſelf to appear at the aſſignation, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was in Tears, unreſolv'd what to do. She conſider'd, that as things were carried, this Duel muſt needs
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:152700:74"/>produce very ill effects, ſince the Relations of both the Gentlemen, would infallibly joyn with the Marchioneſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> to ruine her, and perhaps prevail with the Court to take ſome violent reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt her. She was ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble likewiſe the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> would be extremely diſpleas'd, to hear ſhe had been concern'd in ſo publick a manner, and in a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch noiſe in the Face of all <hi>Spain:</hi> A Woman, how ſmall ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a ſhare ſhe hath in a Quarrel happened on her account, being ſure to ſuffer by it; the publick (which judges of things by appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, without examining the truth) being always ready to blame her: Having made theſe reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhe reſolv'd to prevent their fighting; ſhe had ſcarce form'd the deſign, but ſhe repented it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching her ſelf for being ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſenſible of her reputation, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:152700:74"/>and ſecurely wrong'd by <hi>Don Philip.</hi> With that ſhe gave her ſelf up wholly to what her Anger, her Courage, and deſire of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſuggeſted to her, and with the help of a <hi>French</hi> Merchant, got her a Suit of Mans Cloths, a Sword, and a Perruke. About an hour before the time of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, ſhe cunningly gave it out, the Count <hi>Talara</hi> was to fight a Duel; without mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Don Philip:</hi> This was enough to alarm the Counts Friends, who arreſted him in his Houſe. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> in the mean time went to the place of Rendezvous, and having ſpy'd <hi>Don Philip,</hi> though the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to grow very dark, ſhe attack'd him ſo briskly, that ſhe gave <hi>Don Philip</hi> a deſperate Cut, which he had certainly reveng'd, had he not been inſtantly hem'd in by five or ſix Men, who ſeiz'd both the Combatants. Count <hi>Talara</hi>'s Boy,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:152700:75"/>who lov'd his Maſter well, and fear'd the ſucceſs of the Duel, had given notice of it to a Gentleman who was both their Friends, and having got together ſome other, ran with them to the Gate of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledo</hi> as they began to fight: They had put out their Flambeaus for fear of diſcovery, and 'twas ſo dark, they could not diſcern one Perſon from another, but haſtily feiz'd on them; and having put them into ſeveral Coaches, carry'd them to <hi>Don John</hi>'s Apartment, that the Prince, who is extremely belov'd by the Nobility, might take up the matter. But the Wound <hi>Don Philip</hi> had received, oblig'd them to take him to a Chirurgions, who (perhaps to heighten the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the Cure) preſently ſaid it was very dangerous, but that he would warrant the Cure. One of thoſe who had parted them was already got to <hi>Don Johns</hi> to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:152700:75"/>advertiſe him of the buſineſs; and as he began to give him an account of the Particulars, he ſpy'd Count <hi>Talara</hi> ſtanding very quiet in <hi>Don John</hi>'s Chamber: He was ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd, to ſee there a Man he thought he had left in his Friends hands in another place, that it was not in his Power to continue his diſcourſe. The Prince, obſerving the aſtoniſhment of the Man, told him he had ſent for the Count, that he might be inform'd of the Affair, and that he would take care there ſhould be no Swords drawn. <hi>Don Philip</hi> is mortally wounded, ſays the Gentleman, and we thought it had been by Count <hi>Talara.</hi> They were all ſurpsiz'd at this, eſpecially when told, that he that wounded <hi>Don Philip</hi> was in a Coach at the Prince's Gate. As they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the impatience to know who it was, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> and her Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enter'd the Chamber. Every
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:152700:76"/>one wonder'd to ſee a young Man of ſo good a Meen. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing her ſelf to <hi>Don John,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd him what had oblig'd her to diſguiſe her ſelf; and the courſe ſhe had taken for ſtaying the Count, that ſhe might revenge, in Perſon, the injurious diſcourſe of <hi>Don Philip:</hi> Her reſolution was commended by all, and her courage admir'd. The Prince, to divert his Majeſty with the ſight of this diſguiſe, led her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Majeſty's Chamber; telling him, as he enter'd, he was come to beg his Majeſty's pardon to be granted that Criminal, who had wounded one of the braveſt Men in his Kingdom. The King fixing his Eyes on <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> preſently knew her, and thought the diſcourſe of the Prince, his Brother, had no relation to <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> But when he was inform'd of what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, he blam'd <hi>Don Philip</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely, for drawing that misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:152700:76"/>on himſelf, and aſſur'd <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stina</hi> of his Protection. <hi>Don Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> being ſoon after almoſt cur'd of his wound, <hi>Don John</hi> made him and the Count embrace one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and oblig'd <hi>Don Philip</hi> to ask <hi>Chriſtina</hi> pardon. He was ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to have been wounded by a Woman, that he left the Court, and accompany'd his Brother into <hi>Cicily,</hi> where he was to take Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Palermo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While matters went thus in <hi>Spain,</hi> the Marqueſs <hi>D' Oſſeyra</hi> was in <hi>Flanders,</hi> where the Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot,</hi> who had a deſign to have him marry'd to a beautiful young Lady her Relation, amus'd him continually, pretending to ſend him every day ſome news of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> whom the Marqueſs thought ſtill ſafe in the Covent, ſo careful had they been to conceal from him her Voyage into <hi>Spain.</hi> He fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy'd
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:152700:77"/>the long ſilence of his Miſtreſs an effect of her modeſty, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Letters were to paſs through the hands of the Ducheſs; and he expected every hour to receive Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to return into <hi>Spain,</hi> where he deſign'd to beg his Majeſty's permiſſion to marry whom he pleas'd. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was alarm'd with continual fears the Marqueſs had forgotten her, having heard nothing of him ſince ſhe left <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> The late Duel had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd a thouſand new Tales of her, in a Court where they are poſſeſt with an opinion Women are good for nothing but matters of Love, not a Perſon but was infinitely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſee her; ſo that ſhe could not ſtir a foot but ſhe found her ſelf compaſs'd with a Throng of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which made her reſolve to beg his Majeſty's leave to go into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
               <p>An illuſtrious Princeſs, who owes
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:152700:77"/>her Birth to <hi>Italy,</hi> had her Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>France,</hi> and by I know not what Freaks of Fortune is now in <hi>Spain,</hi> having heard various Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Conduct, had the Curioſity to inquire ſtrictly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; and to be ſatisfi'd of the truth of her Adventures, writ for that purpoſe into <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi> Soon after ſhe receiv'd Letters which confirm'd the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhe had formerly given in her favour, and aſſur'd her, <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s diſguiſe was a pure effect of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial inclination ſhe had a little too eagerly purſu'd. This Princeſs, who by her own experience knew a Woman may, without prejudice to her Vertue, love Travelling, Hunting, and ſeveral other Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, commonly look'd upon as proper only for Men, pray'd his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty he would be pleas'd ſhe might take <hi>Chriſtina</hi> into her Houſe. The King was content, and <hi>Chriſtina</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:152700:78"/>accepted the offer with the greater acknowledgment, as being upon the point of entring into a Covent, where ſhe expected vexation e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from the Reflections of the Nuns, who, though little acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the World, might have waggery and malice ſufficient to torment her. 'Tis hard to expreſs whether the Princeſs was more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd with the good humour and Complaiſance of our <hi>Heroine,</hi> or ſhe with the goodneſs and obliging<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Protectoreſs: They a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed ſo well in their tempers, they quickly came to have an intire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in one another, and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally imparted their moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Secrets. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having one day declar'd ſhe was troubled there were Books publiſh'd of her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures. You have no reaſon to be troubled at that, ſays the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; 'tis my fortune too, with this difference, that thoſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:152700:78"/>you are true Relations of what hath happen'd to you; whereas I have not had a hand in any thing they have written of me, though the Writers have had the malice to interlard their Relations with Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances ſo probable, many take them for true. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Princeſs concern'd, advis'd her to publiſh an account of her Life, to diſown all others, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their falſities; and gave ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons for it, that the Princeſs (who is a Lady of great wit) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd her ſelf to the writing it on the Morrow. Her firſt deſign was to write it in <hi>French,</hi> as a Language ſpoken in moſt Courts of <hi>Europe;</hi> but having conſider'd there are few underſtand it in <hi>Spain,</hi> where ſhe was concern'd to clear her ſelf, ſhe publiſh'd her Memoires in <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi> and ſome Copies of it have been tranſmitted into <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Princeſs lodg'd at <hi>Madrid,</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:152700:79"/>with a Lady of the higheſt Quality, and a Relation of the Prince her Husband. This Lady was a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and one who more than any other, blam'd the leaſt liberties Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men take; ſaying, there was little difference between a Woman real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faulty, and one that's but ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; the Reputation of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being ſo delicate, that a meer ſuſpicion, however ill-grounded, may ruine it. The Princeſs had often, but in vain, endeavour'd to convince her of her errour, and perſwade her that a Woman may be ſo vertuous as to have nothing to reproach her ſelf with; but it is not in a Womans power to ſtop the Mouths of her Enemies, from venting Stories, and Tales of her; which is too common in the World. The Widows ſeverity was proof to all reaſons. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs was diſcourſing one Evening to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> the fooliſh and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:152700:79"/>conceitedneſs of this Woman, and what difficulty there was in dealing with a Perſon wedded to ſo inconvenient and unjuſt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and that ſhe was troubled ſhe was oblig'd in decency to ſee her ſo often. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy'd to divert the Princeſs, promis'd her to Act a Part which ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive the Widow by her own experience: She was fully inform'd of all that paſs'd at the Widows, and had obſerv'd ſhe was very ſhort-ſighted: She was a <hi>Catalonian</hi> by Birth, and would be thought to deſcend from the ancient Counts of <hi>Barcellona.</hi> Whenever a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Quality of that Province came to Court, ſhe would be very angry, and think him ill-bred, if he came not to do her homage. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> knowing all this, put on a Gentlemans Habit; and having taken order that if any came to the Gate, anſwer ſhould be made, the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:152700:80"/>Widow was not to be ſeen that day: She gave her a viſit under the name of <hi>Don Artal de Cardona,</hi> newly arriv'd from <hi>Catalonia.</hi> The Widow, who was ſomewhat ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annuated, being much pleas'd a Gentleman ſo handſome and well born ſhould give her a viſit, and ſpeak ſo much in praiſe of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, (for <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had attacqu'd her weak ſide) ſhe gave <hi>Chriſtina</hi> the kindeſt reception imaginable: Their-diſcourſe was long, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore parting the Widow pray'd <hi>Don Artal de Cardona</hi> to do her the honour to ſee her again often: <hi>Don Artal</hi> promis'd it, and withdrew, and gave the Princeſs an account of the ſucceſs of the firſt viſit. She admir'd the wit and addreſs of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> and pray'd her not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any thing to make the Widow in Love. The Princeſs having vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited her the ſame day, ſhe could not forbear falling preſently into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:152700:80"/>of the handſome <hi>Catalonian,</hi> and relate ſeveral Particulars to his advantage, being liberal of her praiſes, and extolling his wit and good Meen; adding, ſhe knew him from a Child, and that then he promis'd great matters.</p>
               <p>Two days after, the pretended <hi>Don Artal</hi> went to ſee the Lady a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and knowing very well what praiſes pleaſe a Woman beſt, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially one who is preciſe, and ſtands much on her honeſty, he fell a commending her Vertue and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and by little and little ſlipt inſenſibly into the Subject of her Beauty. Diſcourſes of this kind never diſpleaſe a Woman, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Widow, whoſe condition, age and pretences to Vertue oblige her to live retyr'd. She heard all with delight, and the concern ſhe began to feel in her ſelf for this Gentleman, engaging her to eye him cloſer, and more attentively
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:152700:81"/>than before, he appear'd ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, ſhe thought ſhe had never ſeen any Man ſo lovely. A Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in years being more coming than others, at the third viſit ſhe was deſperately in love with him. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> gave the Princeſs an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act account of all, who not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s deſign to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the poor Widow thus, ask'd her one day what ſhe propos'd to her ſelf by it: I will convince her, ſays <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> how vertuous ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a Woman is, it may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a piece of merit in her to reſiſt the Attacks of a Man of good Meen, and ſome indulgence is due to thoſe who are every day expos'd to temptation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſometimes waited on the Princeſs to the Widows, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they lodg'd in her Houſe, and took great care to alter her voice in diſcourſing with them. Being alone with her, ſhe had the wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:152700:81"/>to ask the Widow the name of that handſome Gentleman ſhe ſaw now and then enter her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Widow, tickled with the praiſes <hi>Chriſtina</hi> gave a Man ſhe had a kindneſs for, told her a long Story of his Birth, Eſtate, and many other Circumſtances; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he was her Kinſman, which was the reaſon ſhe allow'd of his frequent viſits. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all ſhe ſaid, found ſhe had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd the Secret to pleaſe her: And not ſatisfi'd with playing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her under the name and diſguiſe of <hi>Don Artal,</hi> would needs be her Confident; which ſhe found no hard matter to attain, by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Commendations of <hi>Don Artal:</hi> As ſoon as ſhe had ſhifted <hi>Don Artal</hi>'s Habit, ſhe would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently run into the Widows Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to tell her ſhe had ſeen him paſs by, and that it was plain he was in Love. The Widow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:152700:82"/>by a diſcourſe that flatter'd her deſires, and fearing <hi>Chriſtina</hi> might think <hi>Don Artal</hi> was in Love with another, and not with her, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd to her at laſt what ſhe thought to have conceal'd from all the World, and imparted the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of her love for <hi>Don Artal,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s advice; who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, that in matters of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhe had beſt conſult her own heart, and conſider the bent of her affections; but that if any Paſſion were excuſable in a Woman, it muſt certainly be that ſhe entertain'd for a handſome Man: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> could not ſay this without bluſhing, and her heart having reproach'd her for having been ſo free in her diſcourſe, ſhe took her leave.</p>
               <p>The deſire we have to prevail for ſomething we aim at, engages us often in more diſcourſe than is neceſſary; and 'tis ſometimes very dangerous to be eloquent. The
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:152700:82"/>Widow, reflecting on all <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had ſaid in praiſe of <hi>Don Artal,</hi> (which yet fell far ſhort of what ſhe thought he deſerv'd) conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, from <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s diſcourſe, ſhe did not diſlike the <hi>Catalonian:</hi> And being through her age more inclin'd to Jealouſie, ſhe reſolv'd to put a trick upon <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending all ſhe ſaid to her was only to diſcover what ſhe thought of <hi>Don Artal.</hi> The next viſit ſhe gave her, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> began (as ſhe had us'd) to ſpeak of <hi>Don Artal:</hi> The Widow interrupted her, telling her ſhe might do well to change the diſcourſe; adding, very ſeriouſly, ſhe lov'd not the company of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo coming: She ſpoke this with ſuch an Air of modeſty, it might have deceiv'd the moſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious. Poor <hi>Chriſtina</hi> found her ſelf diſorder'd by ſo unexpected an anſwer, and her own Vertue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her to approve of the Widows
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:152700:83"/>diſcourſe, ſhe went away much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and perplext, not having the confidence to anſwer a diſcourſe that reflected on her modeſty. When ſhe came to the Princeſs, ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of her misfortune in very lamentable expreſſions, as if the moſt innocent actions ſtill turn'd to her diſadvantage. The Princeſs, who was very diſcerning, and very much miſtruſted thoſe Women who are over careful of outward appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, told her, ſhe had run too haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Snare, and that poſſibly the Widow did but pay her in her own Coyn. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who had been frighted at this Adventure, took courage at the judicious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Princeſs, and reſolving to know the truth, put on her Mans Habit. The Widow the while ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded her ſelf for the good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of her Plot, in ridding her of ſo dangerous a Rival: She expected, with impatience, her <hi>Cardona;</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:152700:83"/>for the future, to take her advantage of the eagerneſs of his addreſſes: As ſoon as he came in, ſhe gave him the uſual reception; careſſing him in the higheſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner imaginable, with deſign to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire boldneſs into him. And as cloſely as ſhe adher'd to her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, her Love made her that day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a little forwardneſs, which <hi>Don Artal</hi> ſeem'd not to underſtand. The Widow, who had a great o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of his wit, wondered to ſee him ſo dull; and was confounded at his changing his diſcourſe, and falling upon the Subject of her high Birth, in terms which would have been pleaſing enough to the Vanity of the Lady, had ſhe not been that day under a ſtrong influence of the Planet of Love, which for the time had the Aſcendant of her heart; and <hi>Don Artal</hi> very well knew it, though he had the malice not to take notice of it. She did
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:152700:84"/>all ſhe could to make him reaſſume the former diſcourſe, and he as carefully avoided it, magnifying the brave Actions of one of her Anceſtors, who had ſignaliz'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in driving away the <hi>Moors</hi> out of <hi>Granada.</hi> But ſhe was then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpos'd for War, and expected a Language leſs Martial, and more tender. <hi>Don Artal</hi> ſoon after took his leave, and the Widow remain'd very ill ſatisfi'd with his baſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Princeſs, ſenſible of the diſtraction ſhe was under, thought it would be a pleaſure to her, to have the liberty of muſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone of her imaginary Lover: and having learnt of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> all the Particulars of the laſt Scene, ſhe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd how careful moſt Women, eſpecially the preciſe, are to ſalve up the appearances, not much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the eſſential part, if they may but cheat the World, and be eſteem'd Perſons of a ſevere life,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:152700:84"/>and ſtrictly vertuous: while thoſe who converſe much with the World, making ſmall account of ſome little liberties they take with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſcruple, are not ſafe from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy and cenſure, though really provided of a great ſtock of Vertue; while the others enjoy their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours privately, and triumph in publick for the applauſe this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit reſervedneſs procures them. In truth, ſaid the Princeſs, thoſe of our Sex are very unhappy in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oblig'd, beſides the ſatisfaction due to their Conſcience, to ſatisfie the World, which is always diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to believe the worſt of us. 'Tis certain, reply'd <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> we cannot always blame them, there being Women of all Characters, who by their ill Conduct draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves very hard Cenſures, and too often very deſervedly; though it muſt be agreed the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of one guilty Woman, gives
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:152700:85"/>occaſion for condemning an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred innocent.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> though they hate the memory of the <hi>Moors</hi> and <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> expell'd <hi>Granada, Murcia,</hi> and <hi>Leon</hi> by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> and <hi>Iſabella,</hi> yet they retain to this day ſeveral of their Cuſtoms; particularly, their Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, their Bull-ſports, and darting the Cane on Horſe-back, Divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> is very much taken with, where Opera's are not known, and their Comedies (for the moſt part) ill. It was then a time of great rejoicing at <hi>Madrid;</hi> not for the taking of a Town, but to celebrate the Birth of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. The Princeſs was invited to ſee the Sports, and took <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> along with her. I ſhall not give you here a Deſcription of theſe Sports which prove mortal to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who think their Valour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in daring a Bull, letting fly at him with their Darts, and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:152700:85"/>with much skill and agility, though it frequently happens the Bull is too quick for theſe Gallants, toſſes them in the Air, and gores them with his Horns; which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times diſpatches them into another World, and generally maims them in this. This piece of fool-hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs were excuſable in ordinary People, who are drawn to it by Cuſtom, and applauſe of the Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; but cannot be too much blam'd in young Gentlemen of the beſt Quality, who hazard their life to ſo little purpoſe, in fighting with Beaſts as they do in <hi>Spain:</hi> where you may ſee them bravely mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Dart in their Hand, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting, in the middle of a <hi>Piazza,</hi> the coming of a Bull madded by the People; and though he come at them with a fierceneſs capable to aſtoniſh the higheſt courage, they bravely attacque him, and pierce him ſo dextrouſly with their Lance,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:152700:86"/>that ſometimes they run him quite through the Body: But you may alſo ſee the Bull ſometimes unhorſe them, to the extreme peril of the Rider, and terrible fright of the Ladies. This Solemnity where this Princeſs and <hi>Chriſtina</hi> attended, was like others of the kind, where the fortunate raſhneſs of thoſe who came off well was applauded, and the tragical miſcarriage of others lamented. The Morrow after theſe bloody Sports, the Cavaliers run Courſes on Horſe-back, and dart the Cane as they run; which is done in this manner. They ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the <hi>Barriere,</hi> with a Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, and light Armour, made (one would think) of Steel polliſh'd white; and have commonly ſome Deviſe of gallantry, or ſome Motto on their Shields, and a multitude of Ribbands of the colour beſt pleaſes their Miſtreſſes. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had ſeen ſeveral of theſe Courſes,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:152700:86"/>and having in the Armies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd the moſt violent Exerciſes, ſhe thought this not very difficult, where all ſhe had to do was to ſpur her Horſe, and let fly a Cane with dexterity. She told the Princeſs ſhe would gladly run a Career, and ask the Widow for a Deviſe, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to aſſure her of her Paſſion. The Princeſs thought her in jeaſt; but our <hi>Heroine</hi> telling her ſhe doubted not but to come off well, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs undertook to provide her fit Equipage; and <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> under the name of <hi>Don Artal</hi> of <hi>Cardona,</hi> went to the Widow for a Deviſe, letting her know ſhe would run a Courſe for love of her, ſince other young People did it for their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, only he deſir'd her ſhe would give him a fitting Deviſe. The Reader may expect one of thoſe witty ones ſo uſual in <hi>Spain,</hi> but a Woman of her humour orders her life quite otherwiſe than the reſt of
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:152700:87"/>her Sex: One ſo preciſe being no leſs careful to conceal, than an airy vain Coquet to make known ſhe is Courted: The Widow refus'd to give <hi>Don Artal</hi> a Deviſe, telling him ſhe was not of thoſe Womens humour, who judge of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants love by the Colour of their Ribbands. I rely not, adds ſhe, on ſuch ſlight appearances, too often deceitful; I muſt have better proof of your Paſſion, to perſwade me 'tis real: (The truth is, ſhe expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch proof as <hi>Chriſtina</hi> could not give:) If you lov'd me, as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, you would rather ſtay with me while they are darting the Canes, and would be more willing to give me proof of your love in my Chamber, than in a publick place: what is done there gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſerving only for matter of diſcourſe to the Spectators. <hi>Don Artal</hi> aſſur'd her he lov'd her paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately, and thought to have given
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:152700:87"/>her an Evidence of his eſteem of her, in carrying her Colours and Deviſe at the Courſe, being ready to do any thing ſhe could deſire to convince her of his love. Were your love as real and ſincere as you would make me believe, would you put me upon the neceſſity of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing ſo forward, and not gueſs at part of what is expected from you? <hi>Don Artal</hi> returning no anſwer, to a diſcourſe ſo eaſie to underſtand, the Widow was ſo aſham'd ſhe had ſpoken ſo freely, and, withall, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsfully, that ſhe turn'd about preſently and lock'd her ſelf in her Cloſet, for fear her tears ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray her. Being there alone, ſhe gave vent to a torrent of tears diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair forc'd her to; conſidering with her ſelf, that having liv'd ſeveral years retir'd from Company, and free from thoſe Paſſions young Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows are uſually troubled with, (for at ſix and forty years of age ſhe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:152700:88"/>counted her ſelf of their number) ſhe had the misfortune to be taken with the addreſſes of a hare-brain'd young Fellow, who perhaps de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd only to fool her: The next moment ſhe conſulted her Glaſs, which telling her ſhe had charms enough left ſtill to procure love, ſhe attributed <hi>Don Artal</hi>'s reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to the tenderneſs of his years, and want of experience: She was ſo pleas'd with this fancy, and thought it ſo reaſonable, that ſhe could no longer doubt but the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merouſneſs of her Lover, was a pure effect of his ſmall acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the World, being new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arriv'd from <hi>Barcellona,</hi> where he had not us'd to ſee Perſons of her Quality and Birth; beſides, ſhe knew young Country Gentlemen have ſuch Chymerical Idea's of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Quality, that they think it enough to honour and admire them, without daring to puſh on
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:152700:88"/>their Paſſion any further. While the Widow was thus deep in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> ſufficiently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd at what ſhe had heard, went back to the Princeſs, whom ſhe found buſie about her Equipage for the Courſe, not doubting in the leaſt but the Widow had given the Deviſe: But when <hi>Chriſtina</hi> inform'd the Princeſs of her anſwer, (though her modeſty made her leave out ſeveral particulars) the Princeſs could not forbear laughing, eſpecially when told by <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſhe durſt go no more to the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, for fear of being put out of Countenance, and quite ſham'd by her forwardneſs.</p>
               <p>On the Morrow the Princeſs and <hi>Chriſtina</hi> were in a Balcony, near the King, to ſee the Courſes. As ſoon as the Gentlemen appear'd, all Eyes were fixt to obſerve their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes: Count <hi>Talara,</hi> as he paſs'd under the Ladies Balcony, put off
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:152700:89"/>his Head-piece, making them a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low Reverence: His Motto was, <hi>Quiero mucho, ye ſpero poco;</hi> that is, <hi>My love is great, and my hope ſmall.</hi> That concerns you, ſays the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> It put her to the bluſh, and the King obſerving it, had the Curioſity to enquire the reaſon: The Princeſs, very glad of an occaſion to divert him gave him her ſenſe of Count <hi>Talara</hi>'s Motto; and added, that <hi>Chriſtina</hi> could, if ſhe pleas'd, perform a Career as well as the beſt of thoſe who were to run. The King ſaying he did not think it, the Princeſs conjur'd <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to make uſe of the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page (ſhe had provided) for one Courſe at leaſt. The young Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch expreſs'd ſo earneſt a deſire to ſee how well <hi>Chriſtina</hi> would come off, there was no denying him, and the Princeſs, their Requeſt. That leſs notice might be taken, ſhe pretended her ſelf not well, and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:152700:89"/>withdrew. Her next care was for a Motto ſomewhat anſwerable to Count <hi>Talara</hi>'s; which, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry witty, ſhe was not long to ſeek: She caus'd theſe words to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on her Shield, <hi>No ay que amar, y me nos que eſperar de quien tienne duenno; 'Tis in vain to love, much more to expect good from him who is already engag'd. Chriſtina,</hi> having ſet all things in as good order as the ſhortneſs of the time would permit, appear'd boldly at the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riere,</hi> and call'd for Canes, but was troubled with an Accident ſhe had not foreſeen: The Order was, that the Cavaliers who preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the Courſe, ſhould tell their names, and make themſelves known to the Officer appointed to Regiſter them, to prevent diſorder uſual on ſuch occaſions. Our <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roine,</hi> loth to undergo that Law, was deny'd the Canes: The King, who had his Eye upon her, perceiving
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:152700:90"/>her in diſorder on that account, order'd his Brother <hi>Don John</hi> to let them know it was his Majeſties pleaſure that Gentleman ſhould be diſpens'd with from telling his name, or ſhewing his face. The Kings pleaſure was no ſooner known, but Canes were deliver'd her: And her refuſing to ſubmit to the Rules of the Courſe, and the Kings diſpenſation, gave cauſe to believe 'twas an extraordinary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not willing to be known. This drew all Eyes upon her, every one gueſſing who it ſhould be. Great notice was taken of the Motto: Count <hi>Talara,</hi> obſerving the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition between it and his, deſir'd, with impatience, to run a Courſe againſt this unknown Perſon, who mannag'd his Horſe very well; but it was not probable <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſhould be as skillful at handling and darting the Cane, as the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> who are us'd to that Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:152700:90"/>from their Youth: And 'tis certain our <hi>Heroine</hi> had run a great Riſque of being unhors'd, had not <hi>Don John,</hi> foreſeeing what might follow, given Count <hi>Talara</hi> a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate hint the Stranger (he was to encounter with) was <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> You may eaſily gueſs the effect this intimation had on the Amorous Count, who was confirm'd in the truth of it by the Motto he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd on her Shield: He could not at firſt find in his heart to run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> but having thought better of it, he put himſelf in a poſture. The Count, who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready run ſeveral Courſes, with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, againſt the moſt expert in the Sport, meeting the Stranger, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended himſelf diſorder'd and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy when he ſhould have darted his Cane: <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> without loſing a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments time, threw hers; which the Count appear'd ſoſtunn'd with, that he fell off his Horſe: <hi>Chriſtina</hi> was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:152700:91"/>founded at the loud acclamations of the People (who judge of things by appearance, without examining the truth,) ſhe knew not whether ſhe had got the better or the worſe, till ſhe was preſented with a Roſe of Diamonds, the Prize appointed the Conqueror. Our <hi>Heroine,</hi> pleas'd with her ſucceſs, retir'd, loth to hazard in another Courſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation ſhe had gain'd by this.</p>
               <p>Count <hi>Talara,</hi> having had a ſore fall, was carried home to be blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which was much to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Reputation. The Count being known to be very expert at that Sport, the whole Court ſent to ſee how he did. And the Princeſs made <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſenſible of the Obligation put upon her by the Count, who had fallen off his Horſe of purpoſe, like a true <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Gallant, and advis'd her to ſend one to inquire of his health: <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> with ſome difficulty, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:152700:91"/>to it. The Count, raviſh'd with joy at the Complement, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd him who was ſent, that his fall did not much trouble him, but he had a wound would not be quickly cur'd. It vex'd <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſhe had given the occaſion for ſuch an anſwer, fearing the Count would pretend to ſome advantages for the Obligation he had put upon her. The Princeſs bid her ſet her heart at reſt, and oblige the Widow with the Roſe of Diamonds ſhe had gain'd at the Courſe. <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> though fearful to engage further with ſo forward a Woman, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd however with the deſires of the Princeſs: She ſhifted her ſelf into her Habit of <hi>Don Artal,</hi> and preſently went into the Widows Apartment, where ſhe found her very much diſorder'd.</p>
               <p>She was ſo preciſe ſhe would not appear at the Sports, but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Don Artal</hi> would be there, and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:152700:92"/>being much concern'd what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of him, ſhe had ſent a truſty Perſon of purpoſe to obſerve how things went, and bring her exact information: He brought her the names of all thoſe who were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred for the Courſe, but not his, for whoſe ſake alone ſhe had the curioſity to read all the reſt: She was much concern'd at the miſſing him, a Woman ever paſſionately wiſhing the glory of her Lover. Her Spy told her there was a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman appear'd <hi>incognito,</hi> and had refus'd to tell his name; and that the King, to prevent diſorder, had diſpens'd with the formality; and that this unknown Perſon had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors'd the famous Count <hi>Talara,</hi> and retir'd with a Roſe of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds of very great value. The VVidow wiſh'd with all her heart, this Unknown might be no other but <hi>Don Artal;</hi> but then thought ſhe, how ſhould a Youth, and ſuch
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:152700:92"/>a Novice in Love, be too hard for a Gentleman of ſo much skill and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience: with that <hi>Don Artal</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the Chamber; ſhe preſently ask'd him what news of the Courſe, and why he had not been there. I was unwilling to appear, anſwers he, without your Deviſe; and ſince you refus'd it me, I had no mind to ſhew my ſelf where you would not be. I knew you had not appear'd there, ſaid the VVidow, though the good opinion I had of you made me hope you might be that illuſtrious Unknown, who ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſignaliz'd himſelf, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd the Prize; at leaſt my heart gave me none better deſerv'd it than you: but I ſee our hearts of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten deceive us. You are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in that, Madam, ſays <hi>Don Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal;</hi> and ſee here (adds he, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting her with the Roſe of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds) the Mark you may know that unknown Perſon by, who hath
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:152700:93"/>had the good fortune to deſerve your eſteem. The Widow, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at a Preſent ſo glorious and unexpected, received it very glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and embrac'd the occaſion, ſo luckily given her, to preſent her Servant with a String of Diamonds of very great value, praying him to keep it as a Pledge of her Love. <hi>Don Artal,</hi> for fear of angring her, durſt not refuſe it; but finding ſhe began to fall again into very paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate expreſſions, he pretended bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of haſte, and withdrew; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promis'd to return on the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, at an hour ſhe appointed. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having ſhewn the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds to the Princeſs, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Jewels very well, was amaz'd to hear they were worth fifteen thouſand Crowns. This exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Liberality fully convincing them of the violence of her Paſſion, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had compaſſion on her, and told the Princeſs ſhe would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſe
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:152700:93"/>her: The Princeſs having ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently diverted her ſelf with the Intrigue, and thinking the VVi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow had puniſhment enough, ſaid nothing againſt it. On the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, at the hour the VVidow had appointed, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſent her back her Diamonds, with this Letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>'Tis time to diſabuſe you, Madam; the</hi> Don Artal <hi>you love, is a Man in appearance, but really one of your Sex: I am in good earneſt, and unwilling to take the advantage of your Liberality, being incapable to ſatisfie your Love. You need not fear me; I am well acquainted with the nature of our Sex, and know it a hard matter to reſiſt temptations; but I pity thoſe who have not the power to do it: be you leſs Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the future, and never fear my diſcretion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The VVidow, who expected <hi>Don
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:152700:94"/>Artal,</hi> had not forgot any thing that might the better ſet off the weak Charms of a VVoman of her age: She thought the Preſent he had made her, the day before, a good Omen, and that ſhe had reaſon to expect ſomething better at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation. She taſted before-hand a thouſand imaginary pleaſures, and began to think long while her Lover arriv'd; when, lo, a Letter is brought her. The String of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds preſently alarm'd her: and having read the two firſt Lines, ſhe ſcarce held up from ſwounding; her ſurprize was ſo great, ſhe fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy'd her ſelf not well awake. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving finiſh'd reading her Letter, and reflecting on the beauty, and other Circumſtances of her pretended Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhe believ'd all true that was written. She was not a little taken with her Generoſity, in ſending back her Diamonds; and out of a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Soul, incident to Perſons
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:152700:94"/>well born, which ordinary People are not acquainted with, or the love ſhe ſtill retain'd for the Memory of <hi>Don Artal,</hi> ſhe had the Generoſity to ſend back the Diamonds to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> with a Letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Though you have deſerv'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach for having deceiv'd me, I cannot hate that in a Maid which I lov'd in the counterfeit</hi> Don Artal. <hi>Reſt ſatisfi'd with the advantage you have had over me, and receive again the Preſent I made you: Yours to me ſhall be ever dear, and in high eſteem with me. I deſire, if you think fit, your acquaintance; and am not in the leaſt indiſpos'd to be your Friend. And I muſt declare my weakneſs is ſuch, I cannot miſtruſt a Perſon I have once lov'd.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having receiv'd this Letter, carry'd it to the Princeſs, telling her ſhe was much troubled
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:152700:95"/>with this String of Diamonds, and very ſcrupulous of keeping a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſo conſiderable. The Princeſs having read the Letter, advis'd her to keep the Preſent, and think no more of the matter; and would not permit her to be further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the VVidow, (as <hi>Chriſtina</hi> deſign'd) knowing ſhe would owe <hi>Chriſtina</hi> a ſpight, for the diſcovery ſhe had made of her.</p>
               <p>News was then receiv'd in <hi>Spain</hi> of the taking of S. <hi>Giſlain,</hi> by the <hi>French;</hi> which very much alarm'd the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> who thought the rigour of the ſeaſon (it being <hi>December</hi>) would have hinder'd, or delay'd at leaſt, the Conqueſt of the place. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> vented their rage upon the poor <hi>French</hi> living in <hi>Spain,</hi> without ſparing thoſe who had been thirty years Naturaliz'd. They ſeiz'd their Goods, baniſh'd their Perſons, and exercis'd upon them all ſorts of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence:
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:152700:95"/>VVhich is no new thing in that Country; for as often as the <hi>French</hi> take a Town, burn a Ship, or obtain a Victory, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſeize all the Goods of the <hi>French</hi> who Trade in their Towns. Judge you then how many Preſſures they are expos'd to under the Reign of our <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great: This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ends in a great Tax laid upon them, after payment of which they let them alone for ſome time; but upon the next loſs they have, the Perſecution begins afreſh, which happens ſo often, that many have been forc'd to withdraw and quit the Country. A Merchant of <hi>Bearn</hi> of <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s acquaintance, and one ſhe was oblig'd to, found himſelf under this Storm rais'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>French</hi> upon the taking of St. <hi>Giſlain. Chriſtina</hi> protected him openly, having ſpoken in his favour to <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and repreſented to him the injuſtice
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:152700:96"/>done thoſe poor People, who ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle there, relying upon their Letters of Naturalization, and with great labour and induſtry ſupply the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural lazineſs of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing them with a thouſand Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences they would never know but for the <hi>French.</hi> The Prince, at her intreaty, caus'd reſtitution to be made this Merchant of all had been taken from him, and promis'd to uſe the reſt favourably. This got our <hi>Heroine</hi> very great applauſe, but the hatred thoſe of <hi>Spain</hi> natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bear all Strangers, made them attribute the favour ſhe had obtain'd to ſomething ſupernatural: which occaſion'd the reviving the ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Report formerly gone about, of her being a Witch, and that with the help of her Art ſhe could effect what ſhe pleas'd. After ſo many extraordinary matters pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd of her, 'tis no wonder the dull and ſottiſh People gave credit to
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:152700:96"/>this Report, while the Court laugh'd at it, and the Princeſs made ſport of it with <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> But her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies would not loſe the advantage of ſo favourable a Diſpoſition of the people. The Marchioneſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> and the Counteſs of <hi>Bena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videz</hi> durſt not open their Mouths againſt her, ſince the Princeſs had taken her into her protection; but the favour <hi>Don John</hi> had granted her, awak'd the hatred of the one, and the jealouſie of the other, leſt the Court ſhould at laſt conſent to her being Marry'd to the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra.</hi> This made them reſolve to uſe all their endeavours to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the opinion of her being a Witch. Having learnt that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> was that unknown Perſon, who had unhors'd Count <hi>Talara,</hi> almoſt without touching him; they took care to ſpread abroad this Circumſtance, and others, to confirm the people in their error.
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:152700:97"/>Their Artifice was ſo great, and their Emiſſaries ſo diligent, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral people of good ſenſe, deceiv'd by a number of probable Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, gave credit to this extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Report. That was not all; for, cloaking their malice with a falſe zeal for Religion, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited an information againſt <hi>Chriſtina</hi> in the Inquiſition.</p>
               <p>The Inquiſition is ſo formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Court, that the name of an Inquiſitor makes them in <hi>Spain</hi> tremble, the ſevere puniſhments inflicted by that Tribunal on <hi>Jews, Moors,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks</hi> there, having gain'd it a high Reputation. The wiſer ſort ſpeak of it with reſpect, the looſe hate the name on't, and the people generally have it in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. As ſoon as any Man is inform'd againſt in that Court, not a Courtier hath the boldneſs to ſay a word in his favour, for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought in as an acceſſory, as they
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:152700:97"/>commonly are who are of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Religion. The Kings Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is of no force at all there; and there is not one Preſident can be ſhewn, where the Catholick Kings have intermedled with any Affair the Inquiſition had taken Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of.</p>
               <p>The people are ſo afraid of them, that when I was in <hi>Spain</hi> I was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, that the Court being met one Afternoon, ſome of the Inquiſitors ſtood at a Window which look'd into a rich Burghers Garden, where was a Pear-tree full of excellent Fruit. One of them had a mind to ſome of thoſe Pears, and ſent his Man to deſire ſome of them; but the Gardiner having refus'd to give him any, the Inquiſitor diſpatch'd a Familiar (that is an Uſher of the Inquiſition) to tell the owner of the Garden the Inquiſitor would ſpeak with him: The poor Man was ſo frighted, he was ſcarce able
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:152700:98"/>to go to him; but recover'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf again, being told they deſir'd only a Plate of his Pears: The Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gher promis'd to ſend it, and was glad he came off ſo. As ſoon as he got home he ſent the Inquiſitors all the Pears on the Tree; and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent being ſo frighted again, cut down the Pear-tree.</p>
               <p>To return to <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors having receiv'd the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, caus'd her to be arreſted; and, (which was worſe) left her in Priſon a Fortnight before ſhe was examin'd: 'Twas in favour to her Sex ſhe was interrogated then, it being ordinary with them to keep a Man a Priſoner ſix, or twelve Months before he be examin'd. However the Princeſs, though ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd to the contrary, labour'd pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately for her, but to no purpoſe, it being not in her power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the particulars of her Charge. Our <hi>Heroine,</hi> who had no reaſon
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:152700:98"/>to fear the Inquiſition, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion, being Orthodox as her Judges, was troubled at the noiſe ſhe knew this buſineſs would make; not doubting but it would come to the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi>'s Ears, and that this, and her former misfortunes, would create in him an averſion againſt her, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters ſhe had met with, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, being enough to draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her the ſlight of a Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: her buſineſs the while look'd very ill. The Widow I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, having heard the news, and conſidering her having carry'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Prize, at the Courſe, from Count <hi>Talara,</hi> made no doubt but ſhe was a Witch; and reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on what had paſs'd between them two, when ſhe took her for <hi>Don Artal,</hi> ſhe was in horror at the danger ſhe had expos'd her ſelf to, by Converſing with a Perſon, who, by the aſſiſtance of the Devil, could
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:152700:99"/>appear in what Form ſhe pleas'd; and was ready to make her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to the Princeſs, for bringing ſuch a one into her Houſe; and would have done it, but for ſhame of diſcovering her weakneſs: Yet, being ſcrupulous of conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo aggravating a Circumſtance againſt the Criminal, ſhe went to the chief Inquiſitor, and told him, that to diſcharge her Conſcience, ſhe came to inform him what had happen'd to her with that Woman in Priſon, who had ſeveral times appear'd to her in the ſhape of a young Gentleman of <hi>Catalonia,</hi> call'd <hi>Don Artal de Cardona;</hi> but ſhe took care not to tell him the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particulars of the Intrigue, chuſing rather to loſe her Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, than to make it known ſhe had preſented <hi>Chriſtina</hi> with them, as a mark of her Love. The chief Inquiſitor, out of reſpect to the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows quality, diſpens'd with her in
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:152700:99"/>ſeveral formalities, taking only her Hand to the Depoſitions, which was one of the ſtrongeſt Evidences in the Caſe. It is incredible what a noiſe this buſineſs made in <hi>Spain,</hi> where they could hardly believe a Maid could, without the help of Magick, do Actions ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſo much above her Sex. It was the general diſcourſe, and they expected every day a ſolemn Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Sentence, ſuitable to the Learning and Integrity of thoſe worthy, and able Perſons, who ſit on that Bench. The people had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſet the day of her Execution, and, I believe, hir'd Windows to ſtand in to ſee it. Some among them, to colour the better their loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> ſaid there was no reaſon to wonder at them, ſince this Woman had bewitch'd all their Generals. The Princeſs was amaz'd at the ridiculous ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhe heard every day of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:152700:100"/>
                  <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> The more ſhe juſtifi'd her, the more they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd her; and the leaſt good Office done for her, was very ill ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the people. The very Court was troubled with it, the greater part not knowing what to think on't, the reſt ſuſpending their judgments till the Inquiſitors ſhould paſs ſentence: The firſt examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was wholly ſpent in formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The Inquiſitors were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at her confidence, and to ſee ſo little appearance of fear in her looks. This made the Reverend Judges believe ſhe truſted much to her Art, or was innocent. Two days after ſhe was examin'd again; the firſt queſtion was, what Charms ſhe had made uſe of to take the ſhape of <hi>Don Artal de Cardona?</hi> She anſwer'd, none other, but what people of wit make uſe of to amuſe Fools: She told them at large, that the great ſeverity, or
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:152700:100"/>hypocriſie, of the VVidow, made her deſire to put a trick upon her, by viſiting her under the name of <hi>Don Artal:</hi> The knowledge ſhe had that Lady could not ſee very well having encourag'd her reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for that divertiſement, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the rendring her leſs Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious for the future. Then ſhe was ask'd, how ſhe could, with ſuch a ſlight Cane, un-horſe Count <hi>Tala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra?</hi> She anſwer'd, he had notice beforehand, ſhe was to run a Courſe, and that his fall was rather an effect of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gallantry, than any Charm of hers. She was then que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd what made her diſguiſe her ſelf ſo often, and in Habits ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent? She anſwer'd, that, having from a Child had a ſtrong inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Arms, the death of her Parents had given her the opportunity of following that noble Employment? In a word, her anſwers were ſo modeſt, and pertinent, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:152700:101"/>being choice Men, and well ſeen in buſineſs, were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of her innocence. And, which is moſt to be admir'd, the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Saragoſa,</hi> who was one of the Inquiſitors, and the moſt preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd againſt her, knew her to be the ſame he had formerly ſeen in the Covent of <hi>Urſulines</hi> at <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſa;</hi> and had occaſion'd the repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands he gave the Nuns, upon his miſtaking her to be a Man: He told the other Inquiſitors the ſtory, and from a ſevere Judge, became her Protector, and Friend.</p>
               <p>As terrible as the Inquiſition is in <hi>Spain,</hi> it cannot fright Love. Count <hi>Talara,</hi> extremely concern'd for the Impriſonment of our <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roine,</hi> being told by the Princeſs, the ſtrongeſt proof <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Enemies made uſe of to deſtroy her, was the advantage ſhe had of him in the Courſe, was ſo troubled to hear ſo ill uſe made of his Gallantry,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:152700:101"/>that he put himſelf voluntarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Inquiſition, and deſir'd his Proceſs ſhould be made, declaring himſelf acceſſory to the Crimes of <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> The Inquiſitors were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſht to ſee how eaſily he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd himſelf Priſoner, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fail'd not to ſay, the Witch had by her Art forc'd him to't. The Count was examin'd, and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer found to agree with <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s. The Inquiſitors would have ſet him at liberty, which he refus'd to accept till our <hi>Heroine</hi> had hers: which was granted her on the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, to the wonderful aſtoniſhment of all Fools. Count <hi>Talara</hi> was ſo troubled he had, though innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, accaſion'd her perſecution, he never durſt ſee her more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had the fate of moſt people in trouble, every one ſtrove to make her believe how much they were concern'd for her, (now the danger was over.) The whole
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:152700:102"/>Court Complemented her upon her delivery, and the King had the goodneſs to tell her, he was glad to hear ſhe had clear'd her ſelf with ſuch credit. The Widow (fearing <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> to be reveng'd, would publiſh the paſſion ſhe had expreſt for the pretended <hi>Don Artal</hi>) Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her friendſhip, and aſſur'd her ſhe had never ſpoken againſt her, but to clear her Conſcience. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> had the goodneſs to pardon her, and they liv'd thence forwards very good friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> in the mean time was very much troubled ſhe had no news of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra;</hi> ſometimes ſhe was afraid he had forgot her, the next moment ſhe rejected that thought as injurious to the fidelity of her Lover, and in the end remain'd ſo perplext ſhe knew not what to think. The Princeſs, who had great kindneſs for her, perceiving her more pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:152700:102"/>and melancholy, than ordinary, did all in her power to divert her, and bring her into humour: She told her all the ſilly ſtories the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made of her Black Art, and gave her a hundred witty Jeaſts on that account. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> ſaid ſhe was not ſurpriz'd at it, having from her Chamber in the Priſon heard the diſcourſes of other Priſoners, of the horrible Crimes ſhe was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd of. Since you heard their diſcourſe, 'tis not poſſible, reply'd the Princeſs, but you muſt be well acquainted with their affairs, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing commonly a comfort to one in miſery to relate and declare his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune; and the ordinary enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of Priſoners, is to tell one another by what miſchance they came thither. I confeſs, ſaid <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> I have hearken'd to them ſometimes, with a great deal of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; but moſt of thoſe who are Priſoners in the Inquiſition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:152700:103"/>charg'd with impiety, or ſome other Crime relating to Religion, they are very miſtruſtful, every one taking his Fellow for a Spy, or a Trepan: Yet I remember I often heard the Complaints of a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, who blam'd extremely the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude of his Country, in retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Priſoner in the Inquiſition, for Actions which would have been highly rewarded in a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govern'd State.</p>
               <p>He boaſted of great ſervices he had done his Catholick Majeſty in <hi>Flanders;</hi> where, perceiving the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Regiments grow thin, he married a Wife at <hi>Conde,</hi> by whom he had two Boys: But the place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards taken by his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, he was made a Priſoner of War, and never knew more what became of his Wife. Upon exchange of Priſoners he was not long after ſet at liberty, and was
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:152700:103"/>in Garriſon at <hi>Aire,</hi> where he marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed another Wife; but that place having alſo been taken afterwards by the <hi>French,</hi> he was carry'd to <hi>Cambray,</hi> where he thought himſelf ſecure: There he married a third Wife, which began to rejoice his heart with her fruitfulneſs, when that place alſo was taken by the moſt Chriſtian King in perſon; that at length, being tir'd with the War, and fearing his perſon fatal to the places he enter'd, he quitted <hi>Flanders,</hi> leaving ſeveral brave Boys there, who would in time make good Souldiers for the King, and was return'd to <hi>Madrid:</hi> He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that he paſs'd homeward through <hi>France,</hi> and obſerv'd that Kingdom to be ſo full of people, and the Villages ſo near one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he thought he had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd two hundred Leagues all in one Town, which appear'd to him very extraordinary, who had been
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:152700:104"/>us'd to travel five and twenty, or thirty Leagues in <hi>Spain,</hi> without ſeeing a Houſe, unleſs it were ſome pitiful <hi>Venta,</hi> or ſorry Inn: And having conſider'd with himſelf that the misfortune of <hi>Spain</hi> proceeded from its being ſo deſart, he was willing, what in him lay, to repair that defect, by marrying again: But two of the Wives he had left in <hi>Flanders</hi> having follow'd him to <hi>Madrid,</hi> and found him at home with his Wife, it anger'd them ſo grievouſly that they had recourſe to Juſtice, and charg'd him with ſeveral other miſdemeanours and impieties: that the Inquiſition ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Cognizance of his Crimes had clapt him up in Priſon, and kept him there, though in all he had done, he had no other end but the ſervice of his King, and glory of his Country. The Princeſs could not forbear laughing at <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Relation, which gave her ſo true a
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:152700:104"/>Character of a <hi>Spaniard;</hi> it being certain there is nothing ſo conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly haughty, as a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldier at his return into <hi>Spain,</hi> from the Army in <hi>Flanders:</hi> he thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the only Man that hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the State, and that now he may be allow'd to follow his incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and take his pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out puniſhment, or controul.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as our <hi>Heroine</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſhe fell into her former fit of melancholly, as if ſhe had preſag'd what was a driving on againſt her in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Miſtreſs being gone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Spain,</hi> but thought her ſtill in the Covent at <hi>Mons;</hi> the Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot</hi> having taken care to keep him in that errour, by writing often to him under pretence of ſending him news of <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> She advis'd him ſtill not to be too haſty, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle patience would certainly make
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:152700:105"/>him happy. But the Ducheſs had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſigns: the intereſt of her Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and her particular dependences on <hi>Spain,</hi> made her reſolve to have her Niece married to a Gentleman of that Nation. This Niece of hers had not yet appear'd abroad, but was bred in a Covent; all the knowledge they had of her, was that ſhe was very handſome, and a very conſiderable Fortune. The quality and merit of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> made the Ducheſs think him a fit Match for her Niece. In order to this, ſhe was willing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour curing him of his paſſion for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> being fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Beauty, the Birth and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of her Niece, would be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to accompliſh her deſign within a ſhort time after her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing at Court. But having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd by the Marqueſſes Letters, the conſtancy of his affection for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> the Ducheſs deſpair'd of
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:152700:105"/>ſucceſs, and reſpited the ſending her Niece to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> for fear her Charms ſhould have, upon ſome leſs intereſs'd perſon, the effect ſhe deſir'd they ſhould work on the Marqueſs alone. About that time it was the <hi>French</hi> took S. <hi>Giſtain;</hi> the Ducheſs fearing, from the ſcituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the place, <hi>Mons</hi> in the Spring might have the like fortune, which would break all her meaſures, and make it too late to execute her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; ſhe reſolv'd to go to <hi>Bruſſels</hi> to communicate her intentions to the Ducheſs <hi>de Villa Hermoſa,</hi> who was very well pleas'd with the zeal ſhe expreſt for the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers means were propos'd to aſſure the ſucceſs of the Marriage, but all appearing uncertain, or dilatory, they parted without coming to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſolution. The Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> went every day to ſee the Ducheſs <hi>d' Arſchot,</hi> who, very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firous to penetrate his ſentiments,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:152700:106"/>after a great deal of diſcourſe, by the by, advertis'd him, as his Friend, that <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had in confidence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her with her deſign of making her ſelf a Nun; but if it ſhould be ſo, he might be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe provided of a Miſtreſs, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the loſs of this. The Marqueſs was much alarm'd at <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, &amp; intreated the Ducheſs to give it all the obſtruction ſhe could, which ſhe promis'd very frankly. Having given the Ducheſs <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> an account of this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſhe found her no leſs than her ſelf at a loſs what courſe to take: But at laſt, feeing themſelves ſtraiten'd in time, the report of his Chriſtian Majeſty leaving <hi>Paris</hi> in ſew days being ſpread all about, they agreed that the Ducheſs ſhould adviſe the Marqueſs to ſteal his Miſtreſs out of the Covent, and marry her as ſoon as he could get her out. They thought this a very
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:152700:106"/>probable way to effect the deſign, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Ducheſs might eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, in ſubſtituting her Niece in the place of <hi>Chriſtina.</hi> The Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot</hi> would not hear of it, as a thing unworthy a perſon of her qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to uſe any Artifice to make a <hi>Spaniard</hi> marry her Niece; but at length her ambition, and the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Ducheſs <hi>de Villa Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> prevail'd with her to reject all theſe conſiderations; not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with her dextrous addreſs, ſhe might trap the Marqueſs; and that the beauty of her Niece, and reſpect due to her Birth, would ſtop his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of a Cheat put upon him ſo much to his advantage. Soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this delicate Project, the Marqueſs came to the Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot</hi>'s: The ordinary expreſſions of civility were ſcarce over, but ſhe told him, with ſome concern, that word was ſent her from <hi>Mons, Chriſtina</hi> was ever day more and more reſolv'd to
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:152700:107"/>take the Nuns Habit, and that ſhe durſt no longer undertake but ſhe would ſuddenly do it. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs anſwer'd her, it would break his heart; and conjur'd her not to forſake him, but uſe all her intereſt with <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to divert her from this reſolution. To what purpoſe, ſays the Ducheſs; for neither the King, nor your Relations will ever give way to your marrying a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that has no Fortune, is but of mean Birth, and (as vertuous as I take her for) hath occaſion'd very different judgments of her: To diſabuſe you, 'tis my opinion you ſhould no longer oppoſe her deſign of turning Nun, it will be more for your Reputation than you are aware of, and this Action alone will juſtifie all the reſt of her Life. The Marqueſs confeſs'd ſhe had Reaſon of her ſide, but that the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of his Love would not let him yield to it; that he would
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:152700:107"/>make himſelf happy to his own ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, without troubling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf what others thought of it, as being not of their judgment who think a Mans happineſs depends on the opinion others have of it. Since you are of that mind, ſays the Ducheſs, I will let you ſee how true a Friend I am to you, in doing you a piece of ſervice more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable than you could have hop'd for, and ſuch as ſhall make you happy all the days of your life. The Marqueſs aſſur'd her he ſhould ever acknowledge her favours, and promis'd to do whatever ſhe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd him to. You muſt then, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys the Ducheſs, ſteal her out of the Covent, and I will undertake ſhe ſhall conſent to it; for her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of turning Nun proceeds only from her fear that you have forgot her. And as all Women are very ſenſible of being ſlighted, ſhe is glad of amuſing the World, by giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:152700:108"/>out ſhe will ſpend her Life in a Cloyſter, though it be in truth only to ſave her credit, in caſe you ſhould not love her: And that you may be no longer expos'd to the freaks of Fortune, or the violences of the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa,</hi> my Almoner ſhall marry you in my Chappel, as ſoon as you have got her out of the Covent. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, overjoy'd at a Project that ſo pleaſingly flatter'd his paſſion, threw himſelf at her Feet, not having the power to anſwer her a word, but his dumb Eloquence expreſt his mind clearly enough: They agreed how all things ſhould be carry'd, and the Daches on the Morrow went for <hi>Mons,</hi> to diſpoſe things for execution of the deſign.</p>
               <p>She told her Niece ſhe had made choice of a Husband for her, with whom ſhe ſhould have abundant cauſe to be ſatisfi'd; but that there were invincible reaſons to oblige
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:152700:108"/>her to permit her ſelf to be ſtollen out of the Covent, and be marry'd without Ceremony; adding ſhe was not to be ſurpriz'd at it, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all for her advantage. The young Lady, who in the whole courſe of her breeding had been taught to pay the Ducheſs very great reſpects, ſubmitted her ſelf wholly to her pleaſure. The Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs having made ſure of her Niece, and all others ſhe had uſe of, writ to the Marqueſs <hi>d'Oſſeyra,</hi> to let him know all was in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that he had no more to do but come the next night to <hi>Mons,</hi> with two of his truſtieſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks, and that he might come to her Houſe, where ſhe would tell him how the buſineſs ſhould be managed. The Marqueſs, who waited with impatience for news from the Ducheſs, faild not to ſet out the hour ſhe appointed. He arriv'd at <hi>Mons,</hi> and went to the
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:152700:109"/>Ducheſſes, as had been agreed on. You ſee, ſays ſhe, what I expoſe my ſelf to for your ſake: But that you may not be blam'd for this Action, I think it very fit you ſhould write to the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa,</hi> to let him know you are marry'd; and intreat him, that ſince 'tis a done thing, that he will write into <hi>Spain,</hi> in your favour, that the Court may agree to it: I will take care your Letter ſhall be deliver'd him, and ſend him word the ſame time, I have had no hand in your buſineſs. The Marqueſs conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all ſhe deſir'd, but had his Head ſo full of Love, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have been able to finiſh his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without the Ducheſſes help, who made him write what ſhe pleas'd, without naming <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> with deſign to take her advantage by that Letter to juſtifie her ſelf to the World, as if the Marqueſs had indeavour'd to ſteal away her
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:152700:109"/>Niece, and that he might be forc'd to marry her, if the buſineſs in hand ſhould unexpectedly miſcarry.</p>
               <p>All things thus order'd, ſhe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got not any thing that might heighten the beauty of her Niece. It was no hard matter to ſet off a young Lady, whom Nature had made very handſome and amiable: The Ducheſs having viſited her a little afore night, gave her new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions for her dreſs, and deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and return'd very well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd with her Charms. She ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed her to be at the Covent-Garden Gate, with a Maid who was of the Plot, and to follow the Gentleman who came in ſearch of them at the hour ſhe had aſſign'd them: She charg'd her by any means not to ſpeak, to cover her ſelf with a great Vail, and not ſhew her Face, till the Prieſt had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd the Ceremony; telling her, it was no more than in decency
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:152700:110"/>was requiſite, to ſatisfie the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the Company, of her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty. The Ducheſs being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd home, told the Marqueſs all things were order'd as he could wiſh. At laſt, the night ſo much deſir'd by the Marqueſs, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by the Lady as earneſtly long'd for, was come; the amorous <hi>Spaniard,</hi> full of good intentions, and led by his paſſion, enter'd the Garden, through a Door, of which they had given him a Key for the purpoſe. He found there two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons vail'd, one whereof was about the height of <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> Having approach'd, with a reſpect not free from fear, he took her by the hand, and led her to the Ducheſſes with the haſte you may imagine. They went ſtraight to the Chappel, where the Prieſt waited their coming: The Marqueſs fell preſently at the feet of her he thought his Miſtreſs, to thank her for her goodneſs, and
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:152700:110"/>began to ſay ſuch things as Love inſpires a Man in his condition withall: But the Ducheſs haſten'd the Prieſt to do his Office, and ſaid to the Marqueſs, he was not to loſe time in fruitleſs diſcourſe, to keep his Miſtreſs from the pleaſure ſhe propos'd to her ſelf, in being at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to look upon him, without wronging her modeſty. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs having his head full of the thoughts of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> fancy'd he ſaw her, without ſhewing her face: He was ſatisfi'd with a kiſs of her hand, fell on his knees and was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. The Ceremony was ſcarce ended, but the Marqueſs cry'd out he was the happieſt Man alive, ſince it was not in the power of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to prevent his being united to the moſt amiable Perſon in the World. Yes, and more happy than you are aware of, replys the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, throwing off the Brides Vail, ſince in marrying you to my Niece,
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:152700:111"/>who might be the Darling of the beſt Man on Earth, I have marry'd you to a Lady of great Birth, and a conſiderable Fortune. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs was ſo troubled at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Ducheſs, and the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing beauty of her Niece, that for ſome time he ſtood mute. Your Relations, and Friends, have agreed to this Marriage, continues the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs; and nothing but a Merit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to yours could have prevail'd with me to have a hand in a trick of this kind, to make you happy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your will. The Marqueſs was ſo agitated with different mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he could not anſwer a word, needing all the reſpect thoſe of his Nation have for Perſons of the beſt quality, to keep him from breaking out into outrage againſt the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs. She was about to ſpeak to him of the advantages of this Affair. Madam, ſays the Marqueſs, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting her, I pray inſult not over
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:152700:111"/>my grief; for I know not whether I ſhall be able to take it at your hands. This was but one of thoſe expreſſions of ſorrow and regret he let fall, which forc'd tears from the new Marchioneſs, who had not any hand in her Aunts Cheat, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Complements from her Husband of a very different nature. The Marqueſs mov'd at her tears, and wounded to the heart with his own ſorrows, went into another Room, and would have left the Houſe with a reſolution to go whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever deſpair would lead him: But the Ducheſs, who fearing the noiſe this buſineſs might make, had the fore-ſight, and care, to make ſure of an Order from the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> to arreſt the Marqueſs; had it put in execution, by perſons who waited at the Gate for that purpoſe. He was ſo diſorder'd, he ſcarce knew he was arreſted. An Officer, his Friend, whom the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:152700:112"/>ſent for to ſpeak with him, endeavour'd to perſwade him to be ſatisfi'd, but without effect. The Marqueſs paſs'd all the night in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great diſquiet: the morrow the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Mons,</hi> where he had long diſcourſe with the Marqueſs; I know not the particulars, but 'tis probable he ſhew'd him the advantages of this Marriage, and the neceſſity lay upon him to make no more ſtir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the buſineſs: which if he did, he would be laugh'd at, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Court, his Friends, and the Ducheſſes Family all againſt him. The Marqueſs convinc'd with theſe reaſons, and ſeeing there was no remedy, ſubmitted to the advice of the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa;</hi> and thought it beſt to return to his Wife, and beg her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for what was paſt. But ſhe would not hear him, being reſolv'd to pay him in the Coyn ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:152700:112"/>from him, and avoid his company who had ſo much ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her. The Ducheſs found all her Authority over her Niece, little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to retain her: She would not afford an Ear to any thing could be ſaid for him, who had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt himſelf ſorry he had marry'd her.</p>
               <p>A beautiful Lady hath great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, her Complaints are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, her Reproaches wound to the quick, and her Tears find com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in the ſtonieſt heart. The Marqueſs, who had approach'd his Lady with a great deal of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, was ſo ſenſible of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, her Reproaches and Tears, that he fell on his knees, proteſting the Crime ſhe thought him guilty of, a pure effect of his aſtoniſhment; and that if ſhe would vouchſafe him the hearing, he could eaſily clear himſelf. She caſt her Eyes upon him, without anſwering a
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:152700:113"/>word; her looks, and the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhe made of being appeas'd, heighten'd in the Marqueſs the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of reconciliation: He made her ſo many proteſtations, and aſſur'd her he would love her eternally, that at laſt ſhe yielded to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Ducheſs, or rather the Oaths of the Marqueſs: But upon condition he would give her a true account what had occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd him to expreſs himſelf trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for having marry'd her, and to abſent himſelf as he had done. The Marqueſs promis'd it, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he kept his word I know not, having not been able to learn the particulars of the account he gave her, which laſted all night; but 'tis very likely ſhe was well enough ſatisfi'd, having never complain'd of it ſince: The Marqueſs about a Week after brought her to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and to juſtifie himſelf to thoſe who were acquainted with his paſſion
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:152700:113"/>for <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> ſaid, it was not in his power to reſiſt the Decrees of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where his Marriage had been appointed many Ages ago.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had not heard of this Marriage, the news of it ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not yet reach'd <hi>Spain;</hi> 'tis certain her heart miſgave her ſome ill was towards her, which caſt her frequently into melancholly the Princeſs had much ado to perſwade her from, by telling her ſhe was not to afflict her ſelf beforehand, by fancying ſhe fore-ſaw the unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of her Lover. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> confeſs'd her ſelf to blame for't, but could not help it.</p>
               <p>Hearing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Envoy was returning for <hi>London,</hi> ſhe acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Princeſs with the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſhe had to lay hold on that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to leave <hi>Spain</hi> and go to the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra.</hi> The Princeſs gave many good reaſons to divert her from this reſolution, but in vain;
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:152700:114"/>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> acknowledging the force of her reaſons, but that it was not in her power to yield to them, and that ſhe ſhould certainly have the diſpleaſure to ſee her die with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, if ſhe oppos'd her deſign any longer. Loth as the Princeſs was to part with our <hi>Heroine,</hi> ſhe was however forc'd to let her go, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the mortal effects of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair: She gave her a Letter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation to the Envoy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating his care of that young <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Gentleman,</hi> being a Perſon of Quality and Merit, and very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to go with him into <hi>England.</hi> The Princeſs gave her ſeveral other Letters, in her favour, addreſs'd to Perſons in good credit in the Court of his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain. Chriſtina</hi> having reſum'd her Mans Habit, and the day of her departure hir'd a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Foot-Boy, overtook the Envoy two days journey from <hi>Madrid,</hi> not having ventur'd to go
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:152700:114"/>out of Town with him, for fear of being ſtaid, if diſcover'd. The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy receiv'd her very courteouſly, eaſily believing the good Character the Princeſs gave in her Letter to him of young <hi>Montalban</hi> (as ſhe call'd him) who confirm'd by his Meen, and diſcourſe, the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the Envoy had of him at firſt ſight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Montalban</hi> was ſo pleas'd with the thought he ſhould ſhortly have a better opportunity of informing himſelf truly of the ſtate of his Love Coneerns, that he appear'd very chearful and aiery, which the Envoy was much taken with, but could not let him know it for want of skill in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Language, which he could not ſpeak, though he underſtood it very well. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talban</hi> pretended he had no other Language, but that, he had a ſmall inſight in the <hi>French,</hi> yet not ſo much as to ſpeak it. The Envoy,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:152700:115"/>who had been bred in <hi>France,</hi> was glad of that, and from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſpoke to him always in <hi>French,</hi> which <hi>Montalban</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd in <hi>Spaniſh.</hi> He maintain'd this Character very well, till one day the Envoy obſerving him in a deep ſtudy, ask'd him if he had left a Miſtreſs behind him at <hi>Madrid. Montalban</hi> having his Head full of Love, and ſurpriz'd with the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, anſwer'd him in <hi>French,</hi> he had not a Miſtreſs in the World, and continued ſpeaking in that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, till he perceiv'd the Envoy aſtoniſht at it; whereupon, making uſe of that readineſs of wit which had done him ſo good ſervice on former occaſions, and few Women want, he fell a laughing at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy's ſurprize, and pray'd him, in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> to tell him truly if he had ſpoken good <hi>French.</hi> The Envoy aſſur'd him, a natural <hi>French-man</hi> could not have ſpoke better. In
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:152700:115"/>troth, replys <hi>Montalban,</hi> I thought the Princeſs had but jeaſted, when, having taught me thoſe three or four words, ſhe told me I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd them very well: I will apply my ſelf to learn <hi>French,</hi> as ſoon as I come to <hi>London.</hi> You will infallibly attain it, ſays the Envoy you are ſo naturally fitted for't. Our' <hi>Heroine</hi> having, by her wit, retriev'd the fault her diſtraction made her fall into, avoided carefully all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of letting him perceive ſhe could ſpeak <hi>French,</hi> the better to maintain the part ſhe deſign'd to act in <hi>England.</hi> Being arriv'd at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Montalban</hi> deliver'd a Letter from the Princeſs, to the Marqueſs <hi>Borgamanero,</hi> Envoy extraordinary from <hi>Spain.</hi> The Marqueſs being an <hi>Italian</hi> born, doubted not but the young <hi>Spaniard</hi> was very well deſcended, as the Princeſs had ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifi'd by her Letter: He us'd him with all the civility imaginable,
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:152700:116"/>praying him to accept of an Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Houſe; for, beſides the reſpect due to the recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Princeſs, an <hi>Italian,</hi> or <hi>Flemming,</hi> employ'd in the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s ſervice, is glad of any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to oblige a natural <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to take off the jealouſie and um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage they have of Strangers em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in Affairs of that Crown. <hi>Montalban</hi> would not lodge at the Marqueſſes, but Din'd there every day, and went often to Court with him, where he was kindly receiv'd by thoſe who eſpous'd the intereſt of <hi>Spain:</hi> this was of incredible advantage to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> who were us'd to ſee thoſe of that Nation haughty and huffiſh, admiring the civility and good meen of <hi>Montalban.</hi> But he could not be ſatisfi'd with the care the Marqueſs took to divert him, nor the civilities he receiv'd from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courtiers, ſuch was
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:152700:116"/>his impatience to know how things went in <hi>Flanders:</hi> He ask'd every one, what news from thence, and was told of the Preparations made for the Campaign, the provident care of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Governour for the places moſt in danger to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd, and many other particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars <hi>Montalban</hi> was not concern'd in, nor car'd for: But not a word of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> nor durſt he enquire after him, in particular, leſt his Countenance ſhould betray him, and diſcover the reaſon of his Curioſity that way. His heart miſgave him ſtill, and continued the alarms and preſages of ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to his Love, which ſo haunted his thoughts he could not relliſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pleaſure though frequently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to partake of it. Sometimes he reſolv'd for <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> to know how things ſtood; the next mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he diſcover'd reaſons to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him from that deſign. Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:152700:117"/>with this inquietude, and not able to reſolve what courſe to take, but inclining to continue in an uncertainty, which left him ſome poor hopes of the conſtancy of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> rather than hazard the diſcovery of a truth which might plunge him in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair. As he was at Dinner at the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Envoys, a Gentleman of <hi>Flanders,</hi> newly arriv'd from <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> came in to ſalute the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Borgamanero,</hi> and deliver him Letters from the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi> The Marqueſs having known the Gentleman by name, receiv'd him very civilly, and made him ſit at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with him. When the <hi>Flemming</hi> had drank the Healths of all the Beauties of <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> his Tongue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to run, and he gave them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral pieces of choice news from <hi>Flanders,</hi> adding ſome Gallantries of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generals the Winter paſt; and, interrupting himſelf,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:152700:117"/>now that I am fallen upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Gallantry, Have you not heard, ſays he, of the officious Cheat put upon the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> to cure him of the violent paſſion he had for a <hi>French-woman.</hi> Had any one then obſerv'd <hi>Montalban</hi>'s Countenance, he might have eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover'd the trouble he was in: But they were all attentive to the <hi>Flemmiſh</hi> Gentlemans diſcourſe, who told them, the Ducheſs of <hi>Arſchot,</hi> by agreement with the Duke <hi>de Villa Hermoſa,</hi> on pretence of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi>'s Marriage with the <hi>French-woman,</hi> had marry'd her Niece to him. Oh Heavens, cry'd <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> no more minding the Name, or Nation ſhe pretended to, and fell off of her Stooll. The Company thought it ſome Diſeaſe, or Infirmity, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one ſtrove to help her, attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting the Exclamation to the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Diſtemper, and not
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:152700:118"/>dreaming in the leaſt of the true Cauſe of the Accident. The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of <hi>Spain</hi> was the moſt alarm'd at it, fearing, in a time where poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings are ſo ordinary, it might be thought this <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gentleman had been poyſoned at his Houſe.</p>
               <p>Could one have dy'd of violent grief, I am perſwaded our <hi>Heroine</hi> had taken her leave of this World, upon hearing the Gentlemans news: but a death of that kind happens not in our Age, and ſhe, by the Marqueſſes care, recover'd her ſtrength pretty well, and was carry'd into her Chamber, where, intending to give free vent to thoſe paſſions the ill news had occaſion'd, ſhe had the dexterity to get ridd of the importunate care of thoſe who accompany'd her, by telling them ſhe was often ſubject to Infirmities of that kind, and had learnt by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that reſt was the only, and infallible Cure. As ſoon as ſhe
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:152700:118"/>was alone, ſhe burſt out into tears, and her fancy, to her further tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, repreſented to her a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand unpleaſant things to increaſe her grief, which was ſwell'd to that height the moſt cruel death would have been welcom. After much debate with her ſelf, ſhe thought it fit for her to return into her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſpend there the reſt of her days in a Cloyſter, her Vertue ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her ſhe was oblig'd to make the World this amends for all the innocent ſcandals ſhe had given it.</p>
               <p>Upon the news of the Accident at the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Envoys, the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Montalban</hi> was viſited by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Perſons of the beſt Quality: The Gentleman, who had brought the news of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>'s being marry'd, thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf oblig'd in civility to give him a viſit. <hi>Chriſtina</hi> (or, if you will, <hi>Montalban</hi>) was a bed when this
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:152700:119"/>Gentleman came to his Lodging: <hi>Montalban</hi> gave order he ſhould come in, and the ordinary civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties being over, told him he was ſorry his Infirmity had depriv'd him of hearing the particulars of the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi>'s Marriage: The Gentleman offer'd to make him the Relation; <hi>Montalban</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he would much oblige him in it, the Gentleman acquainted him with all the Circumſtances of the Affair, without perceiving the change it produc'd in our <hi>Heroine</hi>'s Countenance, who had (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his diſcovery) drawn her Bed Curtain that ſhe might not be ſeen. The <hi>Flemming</hi> being retir'd, <hi>Chriſtina</hi> fell again into tears, yet without any murmuring againſt the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> whom ſhe could not accuſe of infidelity. As ſtrongly as ſhe labour'd to confirm her reſolution of going into a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, ſhe found within her no
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:152700:119"/>ſmall reluctancy againſt the putting it in execution: ſo hard a Task was it to diſengage her ſelf from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations ſhe had for a Perſon ſhe had lov'd ſo entirely, and eſteem'd ſo worthy of her affection: After much ſtrugling and ſtriving with her ſelf ſhe reſolv'd to ſend him a Letter, which was written as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I ſhall never believe any one can dye of grief, ſince I have ſurviv'd the ſad news of your Marriage, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſuch Circumſtances as make me deſpair, without leaving me the liberty to complain of you: Was it not enough to loſe you, but I muſt, with the loſs, have the cruel and doleful ſatisfaction to know I loſt you againſt your will? Had you been ungrateful for the affection I bore you, the conſideration of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs would have, in ſome meaſure, allay'd my ſenſe of the loſs of you: But while I adore you, and
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:152700:120"/>you love me, another enjoys you. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the trouble my grief forces me to give you, in bidding you adieu for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. When you know how eaſily I part with the World, you will be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I continued in it thus long only for your ſake; and ſince you cannot be mine any longer, I ſhall quickly take leave of it with very little concern.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having heard that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Envoy ſent a Gentleman with Letters into <hi>Flanders,</hi> deſir'd him to deliver this to the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra,</hi> and tell him, the Party who ſent it expected not his anſwer. Our <hi>Heroine</hi> having written this Letter, found her ſelf ſomewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at eaſe; ſhe weigh'd the deſign ſhe had of entring a Covent, and found it in truth a courſe of Life wholly unſuitable to her humour: She conſider'd how many made their Lives unhappy by embracing
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:152700:120"/>a Profeſſion out of deſpair, or to pleaſe their Friends, or for other like reaſons contrary to their incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations: She choſe rather to ſeek out an opportunity to periſh glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the Wars, than to lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh many years in an unhappy condition, not doubting but the thoughts of her beloved Marqueſs would haunt her in the moſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate retirements. This made her throw off the relicks of weakneſs her Sex had left her, and having heard that his Majeſty of <hi>France</hi> had open'd the Campaign by the Conqueſt of <hi>Ghent,</hi> ſhe continued her diſguiſe, and went into the Army with two or three <hi>Engliſh</hi> Volunteers, who went to learn the Rudiments of War under that great Maſter. The Town of <hi>Ypres</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſieg'd about that time, our <hi>Heroine</hi> to avoid meeting with thoſe who might probably know her, during her long abode former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:152700:121"/>there, conſulted rather the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of deſpair, than endeavour'd to ſignalize her ſelf by Actions of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary valour: She mingled her ſelf one day with a Detachment of the Regiments of the King's Houſhold, who with Sword in hand took a Half-moon, where <hi>Chriſtina</hi> receiv'd a Muſquet-ſhot, and was carry'd to her Tent. The Chyrurgeons, leſs Complaiſant in the Army than elſewhere, judg'd her Wound mortal: The <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who came with her from <hi>London,</hi> and ſtill thought the pretended Gentleman a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> fancy'd he had receiv'd the Wound by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to put himſelf into the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſervice, by getting into the Town: This made them acquaint the Marqueſs <hi>de Conflans</hi> with what had paſt. He was Governour of the place, and having Capitulated that very day to ſurrender it, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> let him know there was in
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:152700:121"/>the Camp, a young Gentleman, a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> call'd <hi>Montalban,</hi> who was wounded with a Muſquet-ſhot, by endeavouring to get into the Town. The Marqueſs, well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the name, thought he might be one of the Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Montalban,</hi> the head whereof is the now Duke of <hi>Uceda,</hi> and diſpatch'd a Collonel of the Gariſon to enquire of his health, and ſee if he were in a condition to be carry'd to <hi>Bruſſels.</hi> The <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> accompany'd the Collonel, and told our <hi>Heroine</hi> they had inform'd the Governour of <hi>Ypres</hi> of his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and hurt; and that he had ſent thither this Collonel, to know if he would be carry'd to <hi>Bruſſels. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> amaz'd at the diſcourſe, was pleas'd however at ſo good an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of going to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> in hopes to ſee the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe dy'd: She confirm'd them in their errour, and having an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:152700:122"/>the Collonel's civilities, as well as the condition ſhe was in would permit her, ſhe pray'd him to tell the Marqueſs of <hi>Conflans,</hi> he would do him a ſingular favour to convey him to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> which was accordingly done. Soon after her arrival there, the Marqueſs of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flans</hi> inform'd the Court, he had brought thither a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Spain,</hi> who was lately come out of <hi>England</hi> to throw himſelf into <hi>Ypres,</hi> but was unfortunately prevented by a Muſquet-ſhot, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd as he was endeavouring to get into the Town. The Perſons of the greateſt Quality at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> fearing to incommode <hi>Montalban</hi> with their viſits, ſent to inquire of his health: But he fell into a Fever, and no hopes of cure. All thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him wonder'd at the care he took to inquire who they were who ſent to know how he did, which proceeded from the deſire
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:152700:122"/>the ſuppoſed <hi>Montalban</hi> had to hear the Marqueſs <hi>d' Oſſeyra</hi> nam'd for one. At laſt he was told, that this Marqueſs, being newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd from <hi>Bruges,</hi> had ſent a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to enquire of his health. <hi>Montalban</hi> was ſo glad of it, that thoſe who attended him obſerv'd a viſible change in his looks: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fetch'd two or three fighs, he ſaid, he ſhould be very glad to ſee the Marqueſs, having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Conſequence to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to him. The Marqueſs being inform'd of it, ran to him immediately, fancying him to be a Gentleman of the Houſe of <hi>Montalban,</hi> who had been of his acquaintance in <hi>Spain.</hi> As the Marqueſs enter'd the Room, they told him the Gentleman was ſpeechleſs. The Marqueſs went haſtily up to the Bed, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtedfaſtly on the Perſon that lay there, knew her to be his
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:152700:123"/>
                  <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> a dying: She reacht forth her Arm, and taking him by the Hand, made him ſenſible of the ſatisfaction ſhe had, to ſee him before ſhe dy'd. The tragick Spectacle ſo affected the Marqueſs, he was ready to fall down dead for ſorrow: He continued many days retir'd in a religious Houſe, and incapable of comfort for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe of our <hi>Heroine</hi>'s death, he reſolv'd to quit that Country where a hundred Objects would every day repreſent to his memory, the death of <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> He made uſe of his Friends to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him Employment elſe-where, and in a ſhort time after receiv'd Orders from <hi>Spain</hi> to go and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in <hi>Biſcay.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152700:123"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
